<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Quakery slain irrecoverably by the principal Quakers themselves, with a spiritual sword of their own forgery, whose names are here under-written their spreading spiritual murder cries up to heaven for justice, which appears clearly in this treatise ... / written in love as a fore-warning, given to all tender-hearted seeking, unsetled Christians, by Christopher Wade.</title>
            <author>Wade, Christopher, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 181 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65609</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33758</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13553785</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13553785</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100246</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65609)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100246)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1558:62)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Quakery slain irrecoverably by the principal Quakers themselves, with a spiritual sword of their own forgery, whose names are here under-written their spreading spiritual murder cries up to heaven for justice, which appears clearly in this treatise ... / written in love as a fore-warning, given to all tender-hearted seeking, unsetled Christians, by Christopher Wade.</title>
                  <author>Wade, Christopher, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 56, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100246:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100246:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Quakery ſlain irrecoverably, by the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Quakers themſelves, with a ſpiritual Sword of their own Forgery, whoſe names are here under-written.</p>
            <p>Their ſpreading ſpiritual Murder, cries up to Heaven for Juſtice, which appears clearly in this Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>The Names of the twenty four Quakers, who are found by their falſeneſs to be Actors to deſtroy Quakery root and branch, are, 1. <hi>Iames Nayler.</hi> 2. <hi>Iames Milner,</hi> the falſe Chriſt and falſe Prophet. 3. <hi>Richard Huberthorn.</hi> 4. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Atkinſon.</hi> 5. <hi>Iames Lancaſter.</hi> 6. <hi>George Witehead.</hi> 7. <hi>Thomas Simmonds.</hi> 8. <hi>Thomas Biddal.</hi> 9. <hi>Iohn Barber.</hi> 10. <hi>Iohn Sparrow.</hi> 11. <hi>Anne Blake.</hi> 12. <hi>George Fox.</hi> 13. <hi>Francis Houghill.</hi> 14. <hi>Edward Burroughs.</hi> 15. <hi>Alexander Parker.</hi> 16. <hi>Thomas Aldam.</hi> 17. <hi>Anthony Perſon.</hi> 18. <hi>Gervice Benſon.</hi> 19. <hi>Thomas Raw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linſon.</hi> 20. <hi>Robert Rich.</hi> 21. <hi>Robert Dring.</hi> 22. <hi>Leonard Fell.</hi> 23. <hi>Martha Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds.</hi> 24. <hi>Iames Parnel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And herein is made apparent to publick view, That theſe twenty four Quakers, as a ſample of the reſt, have manifeſted themſelves to be amongſt them, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious lyers, foul-mouthed ſlanderers, cowardly backbiters, dangerous equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocating ſeducers, palpable falſifiers of the very words of the holy Scriptures to deceive withal, and in print falſifiers of their Oppoſers words, being printed alſo; and bold-faced perverters of holy Scriptures, to deluding ends, and deſperate blaſphemers, they being undeniably tainted with theſe preſumptuous ſins, even whilſt they boaſt they have no ſin in them, and how they have been led to prove ſubſtantially, that they themſelves are of the Devil, and not of Chriſt: ſhewing herein alſo, how the holy Scriptures do by apparent marks exactly ſet forth to view, that the quakers are of thoſe falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets, that ſhall deceive many, foretold of by our bleſſed Saviour; and how the holy Scriptures do prove that the quakers are of thoſe that do act in the great ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, their principal errors being herein alſo by Scriptures cleerly confuted: the two falſe Witneſſes <hi>Iohn Rove,</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Muggleton,</hi> whoſe fancies do now appear in print alſo, who ſay they are taught immediately by Chriſt himſelf, as the Quakers by their tenents alſo do; but it's ſhewed, that their doctrines are flat contrary one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and yet both abſolutely and horribly falſe; and thereby alſo both the two Witneſſes, and the Quakers alſo are proved herein to be all of them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding notorious lyers.</p>
            <p>Written in love, as a fair fore-warning, given to all tender-hearted ſeeking, unſetled Chriſtians, by <hi>Chriſtopher Wade.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Then if any man ſhall ſay unto you, Lo here is Chriſt, or there, believe it not; for there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts and falſe prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſigns and wonders, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that (if it were poſſible) they ſhall deceive the very elect: behold, I have told you before,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 24.23, 24, 25.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Take heed that no man deceive you, for many ſhall come in my name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, and ſhall deceive many,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 24.4, 5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author. 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notes">
            <pb facs="tcp:100246:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100246:2"/>
            <head>Short Notes directing to ſome of the chiefeſt things in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <p>JAmes Nayler, <hi>quaker, detected in my firſt and ſecond Diſcourſe:</hi> Richard Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berthorn, <hi>quaker, detected alſo in my ſecond Diſcourſe:</hi> James Milner, <hi>quaker, is detected in my third Diſcourſe:</hi> Chriſtopher Atkinſon, James Lancaſter, George Whitehead, <hi>and</hi> Thomas Simmonds, <hi>quakers, are detected together in my fourth Diſcourſe:</hi> Thomas Biddal, <hi>quaker, is detected in my fifth Diſcouſe:</hi> John Barber, <hi>quaker, is detected in my ſixth Diſcourſe:</hi> John Sparrow, <hi>quaker, is detected in my ſeventh Diſcourſe:</hi> Anne Blake, <hi>quaker, is detected in my eighth Diſcourſe:</hi> Geo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge Fox, <hi>quaker, is detected in my ninth Diſcourſe:</hi> Goerge Fox <hi>again, and nine more quakers with him, are detected together in my tenth Diſcourſe:</hi> Leonard Fell, <hi>quaker, is detected in my eleventh Diſcourſe:</hi> Martha Simmonds, <hi>quaker, is detected in my twelfth Diſcourſe:</hi> James Parnel, <hi>quaker, is detected in my thirteenth Diſcourſe: quakery it ſelf detected more in my fourteenth Diſcourſe: the two falſe Witneſſes,</hi> John Reve, <hi>and</hi> Lodowick Muggleton, <hi>are detected in my Poſtſcript.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> HOw ſubſtantially the quakers do declare themſelves to be of the devil, and not of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> That the quakers muſt upon neceſſity prove, that notorious lying, ſlandering cowardly backbiting, deluding equivocation, falſifying of the very words of the holy Scripturtes to deceive people with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and fearful blaſphemies: they muſt prove, that theſe and ſuch-like preſumptuous tranſgreſſions are no ſins, or elſe by their being ſo manifeſtly guilty in theſe ſins, they do thereby totally deſtroy their quakery root and branch, which is proved in the whole drift of this Treatiſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> The Scriptures proved to be the Word of God, though the quakers deny it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> That there are three diſpenſations of Gods minde to men, approved of in the Scriptures; firſt, immediately until the Scriptures were written: ſecondly, mediately by the Prophets writings: thirdly, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by the writings of Apoſtles, though the quakers to preſerve their ſatanical enthuſiaſms from Scripture-controle, will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge none other but immediate revelations: which is proved to be falſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> That there is no Scripture, that is ſaid to be letter, that is death, and killeth, but the letter of the moral law, and that onely; though the quakers, to preſerve their Satanical enthuſiaſms, do ſay without any diſtinction, that the letter of the Scripture is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,
<pb facs="tcp:100246:3"/> and is death, and killeth; but that is proved to be falſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> That the quakers do ſay openly, that they are the way, the truth, and the life; and that they are the judge of the world; and that they are equal with God, and Gods fellow; and do ſay plainly and publickly, I am Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> That the quakers Doctrine is ſuch, that upon neceſſity they muſt be ſo grown up in quakery, that they muſt be inabled to account of, and eſteem of themſelves, to be Chriſt, a perfect Chriſt, without ſin, or elſe they cannot have the leaſt quakiſh hope to be ſaved.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> How plainly the quakers do make themſelves appear to be of the falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets, ſhewing deceitful ſigns and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, foretold of by our Saviour.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> That neither Chriſts perſon, nor the heaven it is in, is in mens bodies, but is without men, though the quakers tenents do falſly ſay, that they are within men.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> That the quakers do fearfully blaſpheme againſt the Holy Ghoſt, and his inſpired written Scriptures.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> How exactly the quakers do make themſelves to be of thoſe that do act in the great ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12</hi> That the grounded language of the Scriptures, do not require that a man be free from all ſin in his perſon, in his inward or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man both, in this life of mortality; but that in his integrity, he muſt be free from guile and hypocriſie in his inward man, heart, minde, and intentions, or elſe he cannot be ſaved; though the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers by their tenents do affirm, that a man muſt be totally perfect from all ſin in him, even in his inward and outward man both, in this life, or elſe he cannot be ſaved: which is proved to a helliſh falſe deluſion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13</hi> That no man hath any cauſe in the leaſt meaſure to be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged at the quakers ſufferings, nor at their miracles.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> That the quakers have had at their Meeting, perſons that have skreeked, yelled, and howled; which is the conditions of Night-Owls, and infernal ſpirits, and of dogs and devouring wolves.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15</hi> That fearful and hideous howling, is ordinary with the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourses">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100246:3"/>
            <head>My firſt and ſecond Diſcourſe againſt the QUAKERS. In which anatomizing of the Quakers, or rip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping their foul ſpiritual intrails open to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick view, I ſhall firſt ſpeak to <hi>James Nailer.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="discourse">
               <head>FIRST,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JAmes Nayler,</hi> why haſt thou garniſhed the beginning of thy book, (which, as applied to thy Doctrine, thou haſt rightly named it <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan's Deſign diſcovered</hi>) with cowardly diſſembling hypocriſie, to delude the hearts of the people: which doth appear plainly, where thou dareſt to ſay (in thy Reply to <hi>Thomas Moor,</hi> thy godly Oppoſer) The Lord be Judge betwixt me and that lying murtherous Spirit, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I own any other Righteouſneſs, then that everlaſting Righteouſneſs of God, wrought in the perſon of Jeſus Chriſt of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, Reſurrection and Aſcenſion according to the Scriptures? Theſe are thy words, <hi>James;</hi> and herewith, if no notice be taken that <hi>James Nayler</hi> doth not ſay, That he owneth no other works or righteouſneſs, then thoſe which were wrought in the perſon of Chriſt, without his, or any other mens bodies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for his or their juſtification before God: then who would think, but that <hi>James,</hi> by that this own good confeſſion againſt Quakery, were a very honeſt man; and be ready to ſtand up in his defence, and ſay Doubtleſs, people do much wrong <hi>James,</hi> to think that he is of the Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>akers Opinion, to be ſaved by legal works wrought in their bodies? No, no, <hi>James</hi> app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ars to be none of thoſe deluded Quakers: doth not he his own ſelf ſay, That he owneth no other righteouſneſs then that ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting righteouſneſs of God wrought in the perſon of Jeſus Chriſt of <hi>Nazareth?</hi> and calls God to judge him, if he means not the ſame things
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100246:4"/> he ſpeaks: his words are to that effect in full, you ſee. Then what would you have a man to ſay? can he ſpeak plainlier againſt Quakery, then he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>? But yet notwithſtanding thoſe his hypocritical word, all his Doctrine doth b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and him for an equivocating deluding Diſſembler, by his ſo ſaying: but <hi>James</hi> hath hereby mentally kept open a back-door to come in with his Quakery again, as <hi>Ralph Sherwine,</hi> a notorious Jeſuite-Papiſt did in Popery, who was hanged at Tiburn in <hi>Anno</hi> 1581. notwithſtanding his Confeſſion of his Faith againſt Popery; he ſaying, That in me and of me there is nothing but ſin and abomination, and I truſt only to be ſaved by the death &amp; blood-ſhedding of Jeſus Chriſt. And ſome Papiſts have made the ſame good Confeſſion in my hearing, and yet do remain as abſolute Papiſts as ever they were; as it appears that thou <hi>James Naylsr</hi> doſt remain in thy Quakery ſtill in full, notwithſtanding thy formerly-diſſembled good Confeſſion, appearing in full oppoſition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Quakery.</p>
               <p>And to bring in his own evidence againſt himſelf, that he doth thereby diſſemble, to delude, note, That <hi>Tho. Moor,</hi> his Oppoſer, hath in his printed Epiſtle to his Antidote, charged him, That he, <hi>James Nayler,</hi> did ſay, That as Chriſt bore ſins in his own body that died at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> ſo he had borne ſins in his body too; and ſo that his firſt appearing to take away ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelf, had been manifeſted and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed in him; yea, that death in which it was appointed men once to die, was paſt in him: and Chriſt's ſecond appearing without ſin unto Salvation, manifeſted and accompliſhed in him. And <hi>James Nayler</hi> doth not deny in his Reply to that Charge of <hi>Tho. Moor</hi>'s, but that thoſe ſayings are his. Thus by <hi>J. N</hi>'s own words appears clearly, that he doth not own Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, wrought by him without men, in Chriſt's own perſon for his juſtification, but as it is wrought in <hi>James Nayler</hi>'s own body: which is in full directly contrary to his former ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good Confeſſion againſt Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kery, unto which he calleth God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But yet further to manifeſt his wicked diſſimulation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="discourse">
               <head>SECONDLY,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard Huberthorne,</hi> his brother Quaker, ſteps in and bears this teſtimony in print, which ſhews, that <hi>J. N.</hi> is a diſſembling hypocrite: he ſaying, in <hi>Saul's Errand,</hi> pag. 8. That Chriſt in Scripture Letter without men, and in his fleſh without men, is their example or figure, which are both one, that the ſame things might be fulfilled in them that was fulfilled in Chriſt Jeſus. Now beloved, what is there affirmed in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100246:4"/> this his ſaying, leſs then this: That men following Chriſt's example, muſt have their hands and feet nailed to a Croſs, and have their bodies wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and blood ſhed, and ſuffer a perſonal death thereon, as Chriſt did? But this is but a taſte of their ignorant nonſence. Hah, <hi>James!</hi> couldſt thou not finde ſome opportunity or other, to ſtep to <hi>Richard Huber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorne,</hi> and whiſper him in the ear, and perſwade him not thus to play the fool in print, and adviſe him not to publiſh theſe profound ſecrets of Quakery, that you might make more cloſe uſe of them amongſt your allured proſelytes, as they grew up able to bear them? And had it not been more credit for thee, <hi>James,</hi> to have ſtood up to thy colours like a man, though a deluded man; and not to have ſo cowardly betrayed thy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and thy ſilly dependant Quakers, by ſhrinking in thy quakiſh head, and proſtrating thy ſelf under odious diſſimulation and treacherous hypocriſie? But <hi>James Nayler</hi> hath hereby proved himſelf to be a dangerous diſſembling equivocating hypocrite. And <hi>Richard Huber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorne,</hi> though he hath without equivocation diſcovered his own and <hi>James Nayler</hi>'s falſhoods plainly, yet for his ſo groſsly affirming in full effect, that Chriſt died without men, for mens example only, he ſhall lye alſo with his brother Quaker, <hi>James Nayler,</hi> in his own deluded and deluding habit.</p>
               <p>And now to ſhew how ſubſtantially <hi>James Nayler</hi> hath proved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be a notorious lyer upon his own Record in print, obſerve that he in his ninth page doth charge <hi>Thomas Moor</hi> that he would deny the infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Spirit of God, for giving the ſenſe of the Scriptures: whereas <hi>Thomas Moor,</hi> having ſpoken of the Pope and others that took upon them to give the ſenſe of the Scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ures, he then ſaith, Theſe (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o wit, the Quakers) that follow, differ not much: they ſay it muſt be ſome Spirit of or in them (to wit, the Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kers) which they ſuppoſe to be infall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble. Oh horrible inſolency! doth <hi>T. M.</hi> hereby deny the Spirit of God to give the ſenſe of the Scrip ures? doth be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> only deny the falſe Spirit that is in them, the Quakers, to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve the ſenſe of the Scriptures? And, but for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke, I could and would ſet forth many more ſuch horrible lyes of his.</p>
               <p>And to ſhew how apparently <hi>James Neyler</hi> doth prove himſelf to be a ſoul-mouthed envious ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ace, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at <hi>James Nayler,</hi> to blaſt <hi>Tho. Moor</hi> his Oppoſers true D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in his Title page affirm, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, <hi>T. M.</hi> would with the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> God and Chriſt, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Light ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the World, and that he ſhould no more dwell in his people till dooms-day: but it is plain to the flat contrary, That <hi>T. M.</hi> in that his book out of which he is charged, ſaith in page 39. That the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100246:5"/> Majeſty of God, whoſe Throne is in Heaven, is in his Inſpections, Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and Operations everywhere, and in his gracious and ſpiritual Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and manifeſted nighneſs in and through his Son, dwelling in <hi>Sion,</hi> even in the hearts and ſocieties of his people. Now note, doth <hi>Tho. Moor</hi> exclude God, and Chriſt, Spirit and Light, out of the World, and out of his people while dooms-day? D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h not <hi>T. M.</hi> affirm directly, That God in his ſpiritual Influences is everywhere in the World, and by his Spirit dwelling even in the hearts and ſocieties of his people? what can we think of theſe deſperate attempts of <hi>J.N.</hi> againſt the truth? But he muſt needs go, whom the Devil for juſt cauſes is appointed to drive; and theſe are but a little ſample taken out of his manifold deteſtable lyes and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
               <p>And again, to ſhew how expreſly <hi>James Nayler</hi> doth prove himſelf to be a falſifier of Scripture, to give but a little Sample of his ample falſeneſs; Note, That <hi>James Nayler</hi> in his <hi>Satan's Deſign,</hi> in pages 20, 21. he there ſpeaking of our Saviour's words which he ſpake to his Diſciples: <hi>James</hi> thereto ſaith, He told them alſo, That they ſhould mourn in the time of his abſence; but he would come again, and their mourning ſhould be turned into joy, when the man-childe ſhould be born into the world; and he citeth to prove theſe his words, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.8. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.19, 20, 21, 22. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.16. But there is not in any of them places theſe his forged words, That their mourning ſhould be turned into joy, when the man-child ſhould be born into the world, though our Saviour ſhewed them an inferiour <hi>ſimile</hi> of that their joy at his appearing again unto them, by telling them of a womans joy when ſhe is delivered of a man-child: which word <hi>man-child,</hi> as it appears, fumeth up into the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers diſtempered brains, and cauſes them to conceit. That Chriſt a Man-child is appeared in them: for they do affirm, That Chriſt, God and Man, Fleſh and Spirit is in them. I could relate divers of theſe whimſical forgeries, which <hi>James</hi> hath recorded in his <hi>Satan's Deſign diſcovered;</hi> but theſe are ſufficient to give a true relliſh of his wickedneſs; for, beſides his equivocating hypocriſie, here are his own three witneſſes produced to his face; one proving, that he is a notorious lyer; the ſecond ſhewing, that he is a foul-mouthed envious ſlanderer; and another proving, that he is a forger of new and falſe Scripture: all which are his preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous ſins of his perſonal fact, though his falſe Doctrine be not at all medled with; for a threefold cord is not eaſily broken.</p>
               <p>And now behold the condemning ſentence that <hi>James Nayler</hi> himſelf hath paſſed upon ſuch ſinners, as he hath proved himſelf to be; which is thus: where <hi>James Nayler</hi> is ſpeaking of Chriſt Jeſus in his book he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100246:5"/> calls, <hi>Love to the Loſt</hi> (he ſaith) But who ſays they know Chriſt, and are redeemed, and commits ſin, not keeping his commands, is a lyer; and ſo abides not in the Truth and anoynting, and ſo is of the Devil, and not of Chriſt; for he that abides in Chriſt, ſins not. Theſe be thy words, <hi>James Nayler:</hi> but now <hi>James,</hi> take notice how the Devil hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled thee to publiſh thine own ſhame and condemnation in print, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou haſt rendered up the Quakers and alſo Quakery it ſelf odious to preſent and future poſterity: and firſt, for thy ſelf, <hi>Iames,</hi> thou doſt pretend in thy tenents, That thou doſt know Chriſt, and art redeemed; and yet thou haſt made it appear even againſt all contradiction whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, that thou doſt commit notorious ſins, and ſo thou doſt not keep his commands, nor doſt abide in Chriſt: for thou ſayeſt that he that abides in Chriſt ſins not; but thou, <hi>James,</hi> haſt made thy ſins of thy perſonal act and fact manifeſt: therefore by thy own mouth thou doſt ſtand con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to be a lyer, and ſo art of the Devil, and not of Chriſt: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, that you Quakers do refuſe the imputation of Chriſt's righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs wrought without you, to be applied to you, as being ſinners, for your juſtification; Thy judgement is true <hi>James,</hi> that thou art of the Devil, and not of Chriſt; and this thy ſelf-condemning law being by thee recorded in print, it muſt ſtand firm as the Law of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> to remain as an eſtabliſhed monument to poſterity; teſtifying againſt wicked <hi>James Nayler</hi> himſelf, and alſo againſt all ſuch Quakers which are found to be ſinners. And now under my Lord Chriſt his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, I will try how many ſuch wicked Quakers I can finde out by name, not exceeding an ordinary volume; for it appears, that not onely <hi>James Nayler's</hi> Law will condemn them all to be of the Devil, and not of Chriſt; but alſo God's Law. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.16. doth condemn not onely <hi>James Nayler,</hi> but alſo all ſuch lying ſlandering Quakers as he hath made himſelf appear to be: for God's Law ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs againſt thy neighbour;</hi> but <hi>James Nayler</hi> doth even upon his own record, bear falſe witneſs, not onely againſt man but alſo againſt God, by his forging new and falſe Scripture. Thus <hi>James Nayler</hi> hath ſet himſelf by a condemned man, both by God's and his own Law.</p>
               <p>And now beloved, we are to take ſpecial notice hereto, that <hi>James Nayler</hi> hath eſtabliſhed the grounded Principles of Quakery largely in twenty four ſeveral Diſtinctions, in the very ſelf-ſame book which he calls, <hi>Love to the Loſt;</hi> in which ſelf-ſame book, he hath firmly proved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Teacher of Quakery to be a lyer, and of the Devil, and not of Chriſt, even at that time when he declared in print the Grounds and Principles of Quakery. And this being well conſidered of, what hope
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100246:6"/> or expectation can there be in the leaſt meaſure, that any Doctrine can proceed from him (that hath ſo firmly proved himſelf to be a lyer and of the Devil, and not of Chriſt, even at the ſame time, and in the very ſame book, wherein he teacheth the grounded Principles of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kery) but deviliſh Doctrine? I ſay again, what Doctrine can any manner of ways be expected to proceed from ſuch a ſelf-proved, deviliſhfied man, then deviliſh Doctrine? And note alſo herewith, That the ſame Principles of Quakery, (which <hi>James Nayler</hi> taught, even when he proved himſelf to be a lyer, and no abider in the truth; and ſo is of the devil and not of Chriſt) are received and taught by all right Quakers, as if they were divine Oracles of God. All which alſo proveth clearly againſt all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, That if the Quakers poſſibly could and would forſake their Practice in perſonal ſins; yet if they do not alſo therewith totally forſake their Doctrine of Quakery, which is before proved to flow forth of a deviliſh Fountain, they will remain under the condemnation of God's Law, becauſe, though they be ſinners, yet do deſperately refuſe the grace of Goſpel-imputation; and alſo the condemnation of <hi>James Nayler's</hi> Law faſtneth on them, that they abide not in the truth, but are of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and not of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And I ſhall prove, That the Quakers do deſperately refuſe all Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation when I come to diſcourſe with the ten Quakers together.</p>
               <p>But <hi>James Nayler,</hi> a word or two more with thee, and that is to ſhew thee, how thy deluding Maſter, to make ſure work, hath led thee to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That thy Quakers Chriſt is no Chriſt: for thou being asked, as in the 25 <hi>pag.</hi> of <hi>Saul's Errand,</hi> Whether Chriſt, as Man, is in thee, or no; thou thereto didſt anſwer, ſaying, <hi>Chriſt is not divided; for if he be, he is no more Chriſt: but</hi> (ſaidſt thou) <hi>I witneſs that Chriſt in me, who is God and Man, in meaſure.</hi> Theſe be thy words, <hi>James;</hi> and herein is much to be obſerved, That by his affirming, that Chriſt is not divided; for if he be, he is no more Chriſt: and by his ſaying in full effect, That Chriſt, not onely as he is God, but alſo as he is man, is in him but in meaſure; which is, That Chriſt, God and Man, is but in part in him: then the other part of Chriſt, muſt needs be without him: for he by his words denieth, that whole Chriſt, God and Man is in him; and if he ſhould not deny that, then how would all the reſt of the Quakers do, to have their meaſure or parts of Chriſt, God and Man alſo in them? for if <hi>James Nayler</hi> had ſwallowed up whole Chriſt, God and alſo Man, then he would have left all the reſt of his brethren and ſiſter Quakers in a lamentable condition; they having no meaſure or part of Chriſt, God, and alſo Man in them, becauſe <hi>Iames Nayler</hi> had devoured him
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100246:6"/> all up. But you ſee, that <hi>Iames</hi> is more temperate then ſo; for he doth acknowledge, that there is but a meaſure or part of Chriſt God and Man in him, and thereby he leaves out the other part or meaſure of Chriſt, God and alſo Man to be without him, for the other Quakers to divide amongſt them. Is not this a great kindeneſs of <hi>Iames,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hink you? But thus, <hi>Iames</hi> by thy affirming, that Chriſt is not divided: <hi>for</hi> (ſayeſt thou) <hi>if he be, he is no more Chriſt:</hi> and by thy dividing of Chriſt by meaſure, thou hereby affirmeſt in full effect, That thy pretended Chriſt in thee, is no Chriſt, but a Satanical deluding Spirit in thee: and truely in this ſenſe I ſhall believe thee.</p>
               <p>And thus your quaking imagined Chriſt, whom you would fain have ſtand for a figure or example onely, is by thee, <hi>Iames,</hi> turned into a naked cypher, (o) ſignifying nothing, or according to thy words, no Chriſt, or worſe; for wickedneſs is worſe then nothing. And now doſt thou not ſee, <hi>Iames,</hi> how thy Spirit in thee doth over-rule thee, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute thy ſelf in a few words ſpeaking? therefore remember this, <hi>Iames,</hi> for afterwards, That he had need of a good memory that loves to tell lyes. For know, all ye Quakers, That Chriſt's ſpiritualized and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Perſon of real fleſh and bone, cannot be a meaſure or part thereof in one man, and the other parts of his real Perſon of fleſh and bone in other men, as you falſly imply, (though by his ſpiritual influences, he is in all his Saints) and you ſhall finde it ſo at laſt, if you perſiſt in your quakery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="discourse">
               <head>THIRDLY,</head>
               <p>Concerning <hi>Iames Milner:</hi> I find upon record in a book written by <hi>Iohn Gilpin,</hi> who was formerly for a time a Quaker; during which time, he declareth, the extraordinary, ſtrange, powerful and manifold deluſions, which the devil did act upon him &amp; in him: but he being by Gods mercy delivered, he giveth God thanks in that book, for his deliverance from the Devil and the Quakers. The book is intituled. <hi>Quakers ſhaken:</hi> printed in <hi>anno</hi> 1655. In which book, he relateth, That <hi>Iames Milner,</hi> Quaker, told the people that flocked to his houſe that he had faſted four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen days and nights; and that he muſt faſt two dayes more, for the ſaving of two ſouls, to wit, <hi>Dorothy Barwick,</hi> and the Wiſe of <hi>Brian Fell</hi> of <hi>Ulverſtone:</hi> and he was ſo extreamly deluded by the Devil, that he pretended himſelf to be a Chriſt: and he ſaid, he muſt ſuffer as Chriſt did, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſave the ſouls of the two women aforeſaid. And in a juggling, inchanting manner, with a knife and a baſon, he pretended his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100246:7"/> blood was ſhed: and <hi>Milner</hi> ſaid he gave up the Ghoſt, as Chriſt did: he ſaid he was <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Adam,</hi> and his wife was <hi>Eve;</hi> and that <hi>George Fox</hi> ſhould be <hi>Iohn Baptiſt:</hi> and he it was, (to wit, <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> the falſe Chriſt) that ſhould come after, whoſe ſhooe-latchet <hi>Fox</hi> was not worthy to unlooſe. <hi>Milner</hi> alſo prophecied twelve ſtrange Prophecies, and ſet ſo ſhort a time for the performance of them all, that they were all proved to be falſe in a ſhort time. O monſtrous! what mad, frantick faſting-fits were theſe? But the Quakers faſting need not ſeem ſtrange: for it is evident, the Devil did feed a great many of witches, being the Quakers neighbors, in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> with inchanted dainty food, not ſubſtantial, in an old Barn, not far from <hi>Bourule.</hi> Now do not you Quakers perceive how the Devil rides you, as <hi>Balaam</hi> rid his Aſs, when he would have done thoſe things which God did not allow of? Bear with me; for I have the example of the great and holy Prophet <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah,</hi> which he uſed to <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prophets, in 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.27. And God in mercy hath enabled me to ſee, that you are to be reckoned with them. And <hi>Iames Milner,</hi> by thy Luciferian pride to ſave ſouls, as Chriſt did, and by thy manifold great prophetical lyes, thou muſt come under the laſh of thy brother Quaker, <hi>Iames Nayler</hi>'s condemning Law aforeſaid, That thou art of the Devil, and not of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="discourse">
               <head>FOURTHLY,</head>
               <p>I do turn my pen to diſcourſe a little with <hi>Chriſtopher Atkinſon, Iames Lancaſter, George Whitehead,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Simmonds,</hi> four principal Quakers; becauſe I finde them in a junctual book, (by them called, <hi>Iſhmael and his Mother caſt out</hi>) more open-heartedly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing their maliciouſneſs againſt the Holy Trinity, then ſome other Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers have done.</p>
               <p>But firſt, <hi>Chriſtopher Atkinſon,</hi> a word or two with thee alone. Art thou ſtraggled from <hi>Kendal</hi> in <hi>Weſtmoreland,</hi> to <hi>Norwich</hi> in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk?</hi> I do verily believe, that thou art the very ſame <hi>Chriſtopher At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinſon</hi> which didſt preach thy Quakery at <hi>Richard Colliſons</hi> houſe at <hi>Kendal</hi> in <hi>May, anno</hi> 1653. At whoſe preaching of Quakery, the Devil himſelf did get ſuch faſt hold on <hi>Iohn Gilpin,</hi> lately mentioned, by his leaning to be inſtructed in thy deluding Quakery, by thee then and there taught; as appears in <hi>Iohn Gilpins</hi> book, mentioned in my laſt or third Diſcourſe. But now joyning him to his other three Companions, I ſhall proceed. Their words are theſe, directed in their 10th <hi>page,</hi> to their Oppoſer Mr. <hi>Townſend,</hi> then a Miniſter in <hi>Norwich: And here
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100246:7"/> is,</hi> ſay they to him, <hi>the three Perſons thou dreams of, which (thou) wouldſt divide out of one like a Conjurer.</hi> What, you foul-mouthed apoſtate Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>kers, is the affirming, that there is three Perſons in the Unity of the ſacred Godhead, like the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>juration by the Devil? Into what corner of Hell will you flie next for further directions? do you not know, that God the Father, who is and ever was totally ſpiritual, and never took upon him any Perſon of human<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nature, as God the Son hath done; that notwithſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nding God the Father, is by his own Spirit, in his holy Scripture, ſet forth to be a ſpiritual Perſon; where it is ſaid in plain and full effect, That <hi>God the Son is the expreſs image of his Fathers perſon?</hi> And if you Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>kers be not afraid, that the holy Spirit doth inſpire his holy ſervants, to conjure like the Devil, then you may venture upon it to read the 1, 2 and 3 <hi>verſes</hi> of <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. and there you may ſee, that God the Father is affirmed to be a <hi>Perſon.</hi> God is called Chriſt's Father often in Scripture. And do you not know that the tide <hi>Father,</hi> cannot poſſibly be rightly applied to a bare denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation or title onely without a Perſon? muſt not any one be a Perſon firſt, before he can be a Father? methinks you might underſtand ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing aright.</p>
               <p>And now concerning the holy Ghoſt: Do not you know, that out bleſſed Saviour doth often call the holy Ghoſt, <hi>He;</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>But the Comforter</hi> (which is the holy Ghoſt) <hi>whom my Father will ſend in my Name He ſhall teach you all things,</hi> John 14.26. <hi>He ſhall teſtifie of me,</hi> John 15.26. And if you Quakers dare venture further, then you may read, <hi>John</hi> 16.13 14 15. Hah! what's that? (you Quakers ſay) doth the Father ſend the bare name or title of the holy Ghoſt to teach men, without a ſpiritual Perſon? can the expreſſion <hi>He</hi> be by our Saviour ſo often given to a bare name or title onely, without a Perſon? As for God the Son, you do acknowledge, that ſince his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, he is a Perſon: but know you further, That Chriſt is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>God's Son,</hi> long before he took upon him a Perſon of humane fleſh; which you may ſee in full effect, in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 2. So is proved, That there was a Trinity of Spiritual Perſons in the Unity of the ſacred Godhead, even from Eternity, before Chriſt was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> and a bare name cannot be a Son, though you Quakers blaſphemouſly account the three Perſons in bleſſed Unity of the ſacred Godhead, to be like the conjuration by the Devil.</p>
               <p>And your hell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh language breaketh out ſtill more largely, by your telling of Mr. <hi>Townſend,</hi> in full effect therewith, in the ſame <hi>page</hi> 10. That <hi>he is ſhut up with the three Perſons in perpetual darkneſs, for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100246:8"/> the lake and pit.</hi> What is in this your language any leſs, then if you ſaid, That the three Perſons are ſhut up with Mr. <hi>Townſend</hi> in perpetual darkneſs for the lake and pit? it can be no leſs. Oh horrible! to what blaſphemous height of iniquity againſt the holy Trinity, will you Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers mount? And yet further, to avoid conjuration, you do pervert the Scripture, to uphold your dreamed deluſions: for whereas God ſaith, <hi>Behold, I am againſt the Prophets, ſaith the Lord, that ſteal my word every one from his neighbour,</hi> Jer. 23.39. this place you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, as if all men that are not taught by enthuſiaſms, without the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, which with you are counted immediate Revelations from God: and you cite this place, as if all men that are not ſo taught (as you are) do ſteal their Doctrine which they teach, from their neighbours onely; whereas it is evident in that <hi>chap. Jer.</hi> 23. even againſt all contradiction, that God therein reproveth the Prophets that ſay, <hi>I have dreamed, I have dreamed:</hi> and then to plant in their dreamed deluſions into their neighbours hearts, they craftily did, (as you quakers do) ſteal God's true Words from their neighbours; but not to teach others therewith, but to make room in their neighbours hearts, to ſettle in their dreamed prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical deluſions: and this proveth to be your diabolical conjuration. And wereas you ſay in your firſt page. <hi>That</hi> Moſes <hi>wrote forth Scripture, and not Letter, but the Word:</hi> Herein I have taken you in a notable lye alſo; for could <hi>Moſes</hi> write Scripture without Letters or Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters? but <hi>Moſes</hi> five Scripture-books, written with Letters, proves all your four quakers, lyers. Thus every way, by <hi>James Naylers</hi> ſentence, you abide not in the truth, but are of the Devil, and not of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And as for your frequent maundring to exclude the Scriptures from being the Word of God, <hi>Becauſe,</hi> ſay you, <hi>they are not that Word, which was God;</hi> and, <hi>becauſe God ſpake to his Saints of old, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, or before</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Letter was:</hi> Are theſe good Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, you quakers, to prove, that the Scriptures are not the Words or Word of God? But ſee your wilful ignorant folly in this alſo: for we are taught, that the Scriptures are the Word of Chriſt, who is God; and that ſo they are the Word of God, undeniably, except you dare deny, that Chriſt is God. Conſtrue this place, you quakers: <hi>Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you richly, teaching and admoniſhing one another in pſalms, and hymns, and ſpiritual ſongs.</hi> Col. 3.16. Can you not ſee, that it is not here ſaid, Let Chriſt, the Word, God and Man dwell in you perſonally? as you quakers falſly ſay in full effect, that Chriſt doth ſo dwell in your bodies: but contrarily, the Scripture-exhortation, even by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of God, is this, you quakers, <hi>Let the word of Chriſt;</hi> it is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100246:8"/> not, Let Chriſt the Word dwell in you perſonally; but, <hi>Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you:</hi> and it is in the ſame place of Scripture ſhewed what that Word of Chriſt is, <hi>viz. pſalms, and hymns and ſpiritual ſongs.</hi> And thoſe ſpiritual ſongs or hymns are Scriptures, and they are herein in full effect, affirmed to be the Word of Chriſt, and Chriſt is God: therefore the Pſalms or Scriptures are hereby proved to be the Word of God, though the Spirit of Satan in you quakers, will not ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to that truth, becauſe he feels, that that Word of Chriſt, the Pſalms or Scriptures, will and muſt deſtroy his Kingdom of deluding quakery; and therefore you his ſervants in ordinary, muſt, though there be three ſorts or ſeveral diſpenſation of God's minde to the ſons of men, in three ſeveral ages of the world, that is to ſay,</p>
               <p>Firſt, by his immediate words to his Servants, until his Scriptures were written; during which time, his Servants declaring what God ſpake immediately to them, was mediately their preaching of the Word of God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by God's commanding <hi>Moſes</hi> and his other holy Prophets, to write what was his minde towards men; which is the ſcope of <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.25, 26. during all which time, the Prophets declaring in writings, what God ſpake immediately to them, is the mediate Word of God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by Chriſt, the Son, his inſpiring his holy Servants, his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, to write his minde to men; during which time alſo, even unto the worlds end, thoſe his holy Servants, his Apoſtles, declaring in writings what Chriſt ſpake immediately to them concerning men, is the mediate Word of Chriſt, the Son of God, and God; and ſo in truth are the Words or Word of God.</p>
               <p>And fourthly, God's book of his glorious creatures, continuing even from the creation of the World to the end thereof, being ſubſervient unto all thoſe three diſpenſations of God's minde to the ſons of men, to make up a ſweet harmony in viſibly declaring of God's incomprehenſible Glory, Majeſty, Power, Providence, Mercy and Goodneſs, even throughout the whole World: yet notwithſtanding all this, though the Spirit ſaith in Scripture, <hi>Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you;</hi> and do not ſay, Let Chriſt the Word dwell in you perſonally: and though the Pſalms or Scriptures are ſet forth to be the Word of Chriſt; and though it be not ſaid, as you quakers dream, That Chriſt, the Son, in his eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed ordinary way, doth now teach men by his immediate words without the Scriptures; and though it be ſaid, God, who at ſundry times and in divers manners, ſpake in time paſt unto the Fathers by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, hath in theſe laſt days ſpoken to us by his Son: note, it is not ſaid,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100246:9"/> God doth ſpeak to us by his Son, as your tenents falſly ſay, he doth now ſpeak to men immediately: but it is ſaid, <hi>God hath ſpoken to us by his Son,</hi> Heb. 1.1, 2. intimating plainly thereby, That the Sons immediate ſpeaking his minde to men, in his eſtabliſhed ordinary way of teaching them, is gone and paſt: and though it be ſaid therewith, to confirm that truth, That the great Salvation at the firſt, began to be ſpoken by the Lord, and was confirmed to us by them that heard him; which can be no otherwiſe ſince the Apoſtles deaths but by their Scripture-writings; and though our Saviour did not ſay, Father, I pray not for theſe alone, but alſo for all them that ſhall believe on me through mine own immediate words, ſpoken by me to them, as your quakers fantaſtick brains imagine: but not ſo, though that falſe ſenſe is the quakers killing livelihood; but according to <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. ſo alſo Chriſt the Son ſaith in his prayer. <hi>Neither pray I for theſe alone, but for them alſo which ſhall believe on me through their words,</hi> John 17.20. ſo not through the Sons immediate words, but through theirs, his Apoſtles or Diſciples words, who at firſt heard the Son ſpeak immediately to them, who are to confirm thoſe the Son's words to us, which did not hear the Son ſpeak immediately to them.</p>
               <p>And fifthly, though it be ſo, that if the Apoſtles confirming of the Son's immediate words to us, be not taken to be, by their Scripture-wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings left to us, that then the whole world of men that have lived ever ſince the Apoſtles died, are totally deprived of the Apoſtles confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Son's words to us, who heard not the Son ſpeak immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to them: and ſo thoſe vaſt multitudes of people, have not had, nor have not any means to know the great Salvation, which the Son at firſt began to ſpeak or teach to them his Apoſtles immediately, for them to confirm to us mediately by writings; which conſidered, ſheweth the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the quakers deluded fancies.</p>
               <p>And ſixthly, though St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who affirmeth, That he did not receive his Doctrine from man, but by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.12. and ſo being an Apoſtle that heard the Son ſpeak immediately at firſt to him alſo; and ſo was one of them that did confirm thoſe the Son's words to us in writing: I ſay, Though even he, that great Apoſtle, ſaith to the <hi>Theſſalonians, For this cauſe thank we God without ceaſing, becauſe when ye received the word of God ye heard of us,</hi> (then not immediately of the Son; not ſo, but) <hi>the word of God ye heard of us;</hi> (to wit, of thoſe that heard the Son ſpeak to them immediately) <hi>ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it not as the word of man,</hi> (or our words) <hi>but as it is in truth, the word of God,</hi> 1 Theſ. 2.13.</p>
               <p>And ſeventhly, though <hi>Moſes,</hi> that admired pen-man of God's Works
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100246:9"/> for us, and minde to us, hath diſcovered in his Scripture-writings, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of God's wonderful Works which he wrought in his firſt five days-works of Creation, which were all paſt before any man had any being, or before man was; and therefore could not poſſibly be taught to <hi>Moſes</hi> by any man, but onely by God's teaching of him: and though all this of God's immediate teaching <hi>Moſes,</hi> appeareth in his recorded written Scriptures; yet, even yet, I ſay, notwithſtanding all theſe, and many more ſuch-like infallible inſpired Scripture-Teſtimonies of God, which do firmly prove, That the holy Scriptures are in truth the mediate Word of God to us; yet, ſay, (by experiences which God hath formerly, for my humiliation and inſtruction, permitted Satan to act in my body for a time, even the ſame ſtrong deluſions in kinde, which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan acts in your quakers bodies, though my heavenly Father in great mercy hath delivered me from them) yet I know, that your quakers dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical ſpirit in you, will not permit you to acknowledge that truth, though he doth give you leave, frequently to affirm. That the Scriptures are true; as the Devil of old ſpake ſome truths, to uſher in his manifold deceits, even ſo he over-powers you quakers, though you ſay, the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are true, yet to deny the Scriptures to be any help in ſaving teachings; and are led to deny, in that reſpect, the ſecond diſpenſation of God's minde to men declared in the writings of his holy Prophets; and alſo God's third diſpenſation of his minde to men, by his inſpired wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings manifeſted by his holy Apoſtles. And as he thereby limits the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme holy One, ſo he over-rules you, to acknowledge but one diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God's minde unto the ſons of men. And, that by this his firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of his minde to men, by his immediate words, that ſo the devil, the father of lyes, (by his ſervants, quakers) may make elbow-room for his enthuſiaſms to teach men crafty devices cloſely contrived, both to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves and others alſo; and that his freedom in this deſtructive way, may not be diſturbed by the contradiction or controle of holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, he hath taught you the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dieſt way to pleaſe him; and you as cheerfully imploy your ſelves in his buſineſs.</p>
               <p>And thus you four principal quakers, have made your ſpiritual peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lential infectious black ſpots appear upon you to publick view: and your brother quaker <hi>James Nayler</hi>'s condemning Law aforeſaid looks very fiercely upon you, I'll warrant you, to juſtifie that you all are of the devil, and not of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And herewith know, you quakers, That we your Oppoſers, do not truſt to, nor expect to be taught by the Letter of the Scriptures, written with ink on paper, as you ſhrawme out againſt your Oppoſites; but by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100246:10"/> the Spirit of Chriſt, therewith, and thereon attending, even on his Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, to convey his minde therein recorded, into the hearts of all ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-hearted, contrite, humble perſons, that do abidingly wait upon his teachings: for Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>Go ye, and teach all nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the holy Ghoſt:</hi> (though you quakers account this Doctrine to be like conjuration by the devil) but Chriſt did then promiſe them, ſaying, <hi>And lo, I am with you alway<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> even to the end of the world.</hi> And it is well known, That Chriſt was with them perſonally but a ſmall time, and their action of verbal miniſtration, died with their bodies: therefore Chriſt's promiſe is, by his Spirit to be with their Scripture-written-Miniſtration always, even to the end of the world: which teaching of Chriſt's Spirit in and with thoſe ſacred Scriptures, is our rejoycings, though you quakers, to advance your enthuſiaſms, do turn that kinde of teaching into your own everlaſting deſtruction.</p>
               <p>And now, conſidering it is your ſtrongeſt refuge to lurk in, to defend your ſatanical immediate enthuſiaſms, without the Scripture, frequently to cry down the teaching-uſe of the Letter of the Scriptures; to which frantick end, you in the 7 <hi>pag.</hi> of <hi>Saul's Errand,</hi> do affirm, That the Letter of the Scripture is carnal, and the Letter is death, and killeth: and in this your ſaying, you make no diſtinction in the Scripture-Letter, but that all of it is carnal, and death, and killeth; and yet you affirm con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, that the Scriptures are true; and ſo hereby you do affirm, That the truth is carnal, and is death, and killeth. And now what other non-ſence will you ſpatter out next in the tail of this? And in the 21 <hi>p.</hi> of your <hi>Satan's Deſign,</hi> you to defend your lye, do ſay the truth, That <hi>the Apoſtles was not Miniſters of the Letter but of the Spirit.</hi> But why ſo, you brain-ſick quakers? but onely becauſe you are falſly given to underſtand out of the Air, by your high immediate enthuſiaſms, that all your affirmed true Scripture-Letter, is all of it carnal-letter, and is death, and killeth.</p>
               <p>But now with amazement do all you quakers behold, even to your everlaſting ſhame and perdition, That God's own inſpired Word, his holy Scriptures, do as it were fiercely flie at your impudent faces, rebuking you, and telling you plainly, That there is no Scripture-Letter, that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Letter, that is carnal, and death, and killeth; but onely and alone the letter of the moral Law, which was written and engraven in ſtone; and that Law-letter onely, and none other Scripture-Letter whatſoever, is called the Letter that is carnal, and death, and killeth. See this firmly proved againſt you quakers, even by your own choſen place of Scripture,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100246:10"/> which you have cited, you endeavouring thereby to prove your great hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh lye aforeſaid, to be true: and this your pick'd place, is <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.16. (and is written of Chriſt, ſaying in the 15 <hi>verſ.</hi>) That <hi>after the ſimilitude of Melchiſede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, there ariſeth another prieſt:</hi> and then in <hi>v.</hi> 16. which is the <hi>verſe</hi> by them cited, it is ſaid, <hi>Who is made not after the law of a carnal commandment.</hi> And it is further written thus: <hi>For the law made nothing perfect, but the bringing in of a better hope did, by the which we draw nigh unto God,</hi> verſ. 19. So herein we have ſet forth plainly to our view, that the Law onely is there called the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that is carnal: and that other Scriptures is in plain and full effect, ſaid to be the bringing in of a better hope, teſtified in the Scripture by and in the Letter of the New Teſtament (or Goſpel) of which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were made able Miniſters, as is ſhewed in full effect in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. and not of the Letter of the Law, or carnal Commandment, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid: <hi>For there is verily a diſannulling of the commandment going before for the weakneſs and unprofitableneſs thereof, Heb.</hi> 7.18. which is the very next <hi>verſe</hi> but one to the quakers cited <hi>verſe.</hi> So that hereby the devil your Tutor, as it appeareth, after he hath hoodwink'd you, then according to his own habitual deceitful tricks, he hath led you as it were by the noſe to ſpie out that place, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.16. and to make uſe of it, to ſhew againſt your ſelves, to your perpetual ſhame, that the Letter of the Law onely includes the Commandment, which is in Scripture called carnal.</p>
               <p>Thus far concerning your affirming, That the Letter of the Scripture, without diſtinction, is a carnal Letter, which by your own proof is proved to be a helliſh lye. And now again, you quakers, concerning your other falſe words, affirming, That the Scripture-Letter is death, and killeth: and to prove theſe to be as falſe alſo, I ſhall further note what is written, where it's ſaid, <hi>Who alſo hath made us able miniſters of the New Teſtament, not of the letter, (of the law of a carnal command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as before) <hi>but of the ſpirit: for the letter (the law of the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal commandment) killeth, but the Spirit giveth life,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.6, And now here again that ſaying of yours, you quakers, is brought upon the tenter-hooks: where, though you ſay, That <hi>the Apoſtles were not Miniſters of the Letter, but of the Spirit;</hi> and that's true: But here's your torment augmented, by your tormenting the truth of that <hi>verſe;</hi> by your thereby ſignifying, That the Apoſtles were Miniſters to teach men onely to look for the immediate ſpeakings of the Spirit to and in them; and ſo you would repeat over again your old ſatanical ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Beads, to deſtroy the third diſpenſation of God's minde by his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100246:11"/> inſpired Scriptures written for mens mediate teachings by his Apoſtles, which their writings do contain in them, literally the Letter and Letters of the New Teſtament or Goſpel, of which the Apoſtles were able Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; and upon which the Apoſtles written Teſtimonies, Chriſt by his Spirit, by his own promiſe is alwayes with them, even to the end of the World, to convey the benefit of that written New Teſtament, unto all humble waiters upon him therein, which is before lately proved; and your old helliſh long now repeated againſt God's third written diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, is alſo in this my fourth Diſcourſe by Scripture-truths totally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded.</p>
               <p>And now to prove even againſt all denial, That the Devil your Tutor befools your underſtandings, to make uſe of that ſaying, <hi>Not of the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; for the letter killeth;</hi> as if thereby were declared, That the whole Letter of the Scriptures, is carnal, and death, and killeth; but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found that alſo, it is proved plainly and firmly, that next after it is ſaid, <hi>God hath made us able miniſters of the New Teſtament; not of the letter, for the letter killeth:</hi> then to ſhew, even to publick view, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly and apparently, what that letter is that is death, it is written im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately thereto in the very next <hi>verſe,</hi> thus: <hi>But if the miniſtration of death, written and engraven in ſtone, was gloriou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> And it is well known, you ſilly quakers, That the Letter of the moral Law onely, are the Letter which God did write with his own finger in ſtone on Mount <hi>Sinai.</hi> Thus ſtrongly, your confounding of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e whole Letter of the New Teſtament, or Goſpel, of which the Apoſtles were made able Miniſters, with the Letter of the Law written and engraven in ſtone, which is called the miniſtration of death, and the miniſtration of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, <hi>verſe</hi> 9. of which killing, condemning Letter, the Apoſtles were not not made Miniſters, promiſcuouſly and confuſedly, as if the Letter of them both, are the Letter that is carnal, death, and killeth, is by the force of your own Scripture-words, by you uſed and abuſed, totally confounded for ever, and thereby ſent back to the infernal den, in which it was hatched: for the New Teſtament is there ſaid to be <hi>the miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit,</hi> verſ. 8. and <hi>the holding forth the word of life,</hi> Phil. 2.16. becauſe the very Letter of the New Teſtament, or Goſpel, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth in it the mediate, inſpired, teaching, written Word of Chriſt, the Word that was and is God; and the Letter of the Law is in compariſon to the Letter of the New Teſtament, or Goſpel, affirmed to be <hi>the oldneſs of the letter,</hi> Rom. 7.6. Do you quakers ranſack thorow the whole Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, &amp; ſee if you can find any Scripture that is called the letter that is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, death, &amp; killeth; and it is not declared therewith, That it is the letter of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100246:11"/> the Law onely. And how having ſhewed how powerfully my Lord Jeſus hath torn down this your refuge; and with his written Word and Sword of his Spirit, hath hewed in pieces your murthering <hi>Agag,</hi> that would have murthered the holy mediate teaching uſe of the whole Scripture-letter. I ſhall proceed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="discourse">
               <head>FIFTHLY,</head>
               <p>I do direct my pen to diſcourſe with <hi>Thomas Biddal</hi> quaker, who alſo with the four former audacious quakers, doth deny the Scriptures to be the Word of God; for he being with me, I cited to him this place: <hi>And take the helmet of ſalvation, and the ſword of the Spirit, which is the word of God,</hi> Epheſ. 6.17. I then telling him, <hi>That the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word of God is the ſword of the Spirit, but is not the Spirit it ſelf, and that the Scriptures are the Spirits word, and ſpiritual ſword alſo.</hi> But he anſwered me ſaying, <hi>That the Spirit, and the ſword of the Spirit, are both one and the ſelf-ſame thing.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, A man is his ſword, and his ſword is the man. And theſe ridiculous ſhifts, they are inforced to make, for fear the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures ſhould be proved to be the Word of God: but, to their perpetual ſhame, our Saviour Chriſt, though he was furniſhed in himſelf with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabundant ability, to have confuted and confounded the devil. If he had but ſaid, I, Jeſus, ſay unto thee Satan: yet, for our examples, he would not conflict againſt the devil with his own all-ſufficient ſpiritual power onely, without his Scripture-ſword: but to confound the devil withal, he takes up his Spirits never-failing ſword, his written Scriptures, and therewith he enters the liſts againſt his powerful, ſpiritual, inverate enemy, the devil; and overthrows him with that his Word and written ſword, by his ſaying to the devil in his perverting of Scriptuers againſt him: <hi>Thus it is written, Thus it is written, Thus it is written, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan:</hi> and by his confounding the devil therewith, he gratiouſly teacheth us, even by his own example, by the ſpirit of Faith to take up his Spirits never-failing word and ſword the holy Scriptures, and to fight valiantly and undantedly therewith, againſt the devil himſelf in his temptations; and alſo againſt the deluding aſſaults of <hi>Thomas Biddal,</hi> and all other brain-ſick quakers, Satans officious ſervants.</p>
               <p>And accordingly, the Apoſtles did lay aſide all their glorious heavenly raptures and viſions in caſe of teaching men, and confirmed their ſayings, with our Saviours infallible word and ſword, the Scriptures; frequently ſaying: <hi>Thus ſaith the Scriptures.</hi> But what ſaith the Scriptures? <hi>It
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100246:12"/> is written;</hi> and ſuch-like expreſſions. And it is well known, That the Apoſtles were better taught then any quaker whatſoever.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Thomas Biddal,</hi> what infernal ſpirit taught thee to boaſt, That thy large railing, ſeducing letters, directed to me and others, were written from thee to us, from the Spirit of the Lord, as if thou hadſt been a Meſſenger ſent to us immediately from the Lord; whereas, to thy ſhame, the ſame queries, that thou therein makeſt, appear in the ſame words and form in a printed book, written by another man, to thy hand, before thou wroteſt thy lying letters to us. Thus thy Luciferian aſpiring pride appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth further, even to publick view.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Thomas Biddal,</hi> whither were thy giddy brains ranged, when thou ſaidſt in my hearing, That <hi>Faith and Chriſt are one and the ſame thing;</hi> as thou didſt ſay, That <hi>the Spirit and the ſword of the Spirit are one and the ſame thing?</hi> What now <hi>Thomas?</hi> canſt thou not creep out of the road-way to hell? wouldſt thou make people believe thy falſe ſpirit, that when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>We preach Chriſt crucified,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.23. that <hi>Paul</hi> and other Saints meant to have ſaid (if they had not forgot it) We preach Faith and it crucified? What, <hi>Thomas,</hi> was Faith crucified for thee? If thou ſaiſt, That Faith is crucified to death in thee, I ſhall readily believe thee, <hi>Thomas,</hi> though thoſe thy ſayings are to be abhorred.</p>
               <p>And now to ſum up together thine own begotten titles, without addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them, thou haſt proved thy ſelf to be a very ignorant perſon, a notorious lyer, a proud luciferian, and an audacious perverter of holy Scriptures; and thereby art an enemy to God and his Truths, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alſo, art a Traytor to mens ſouls. And becauſe you quakers do refuſe the Goſpel-imputation, thou art not onely fallen under the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal condemnation of God's Law, but alſo thy brother quaker, <hi>James Nayler</hi>'s condemning ſentence aforeſaid, faſtens upon thee, <hi>Thomas;</hi> proving, thou art a lyer, and abides not in the truth, but art of the devil, and not of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Doubtleſs, <hi>Thomas,</hi> God had formerly given thee, and others by thee, a fair forewarning to avoid theſe deluſions of the devil: for thou, <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Biddal,</hi> ſome yeers now paſt, was (as appears) inforced by the devil, openly to declare, That thou wert one of the two witneſſes of God mentioned in the Revelations, and thou didſt thereupon make uſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man's new ſackin-cloth which lay by him, ſo far as to carry it to a Taylor, a neighbour of thine, thou knoweſt to whom: and thou, <hi>Tho. Biddal,</hi> didſt then lay a heavy ſevere charge upon that Taylor to make thee a ſuit of aparrel of that ſack-cloth by ſuch a day, being within a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100246:12"/> little while after, that it might be ready at that day for thee to put on, and to propheſie in, as being one of the two witneſſes aforeſaid, then ſent from God: But that neighbour of thine, the Taylor, prudently diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that thou wert deluded, though he took the ſack-cloth of thee, to ſatisfie thy preſent reſolute humour, yet he totally neglected to make thy ſackcloth-ſuit; and then the height of that luciferian pride, fell; and thy hot prophecying zeal, as being one of thoſe two witneſſes ſent from God, was ſquaſhed; and thy heavy charges laid upon thy neighbour, the Taylor, vaniſhed away, as if thy ſuit of ſackcloth, not being made, did (as <hi>Samſons</hi> hair being cut) cut off the ſtrength of thy prophetical witneſs-bearing for God, from whom, thou ſaidſt, thou wert then ſent. But yet the fickle unſettleneſs of thy brain, for ought I do diſcern, doth ſtill remain with thee unto this day: and this ſhould be alſo a forewarning to the two lofty and falſe pretended witneſſes of God, now marching abroad in print, named in the latter end of this Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>And, <hi>Thomas,</hi> thou being drowned in ſuch a fantaſtical fancy, haſt, acrording to <hi>James Nayler</hi>'s quakiſh humour, belyed and ſlandered <hi>Thomas Moor,</hi> that he would preach Chriſt out of his Saints: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in that very page out of which thou chargeſt him, <hi>pag.</hi> 32. <hi>Thomas Moor,</hi> there ſpeaking of Chriſt, ſaith, <hi>That perſon that is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally abſent from the believer, is dwelling</hi> (note that) <hi>in the believers heart, by faith of and in him.</hi> And thus thy lyes ſwarm about viſibly, and <hi>James Nayler</hi>'s ſentence of condemnation, pronounced by him a-againſt ſuch lying ſlanderers, layeth alſo faſt hold on thee, <hi>Thomas,</hi> for things alſo, that thou art of the devil and, not of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="discourse">
               <head>SIXTHLY,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Barber</hi> quaker, being as ignorant as the moſt fooliſh of them; but as brisk as the moſt perkeſt of them, his faith hanging on his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, <hi>Thomas Biddal</hi>'s lips. But <hi>John,</hi> why doſt thou run after to diſperce quakiſh lyes: for thou having gotten ſome of <hi>James Nayler</hi>'s lying Libels by him framed againſt <hi>Thomas Moor</hi> his Oppoſer, thou didſt ſay unto one man, unto whom thou didſt deliver one of thoſe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing books, <hi>There thou maiſt read,</hi> ſaidſt thou, <hi>that</hi> Thomas Moor <hi>hath told forty eight lyes:</hi> but now <hi>James Nayler,</hi> being firmly proved to be the lyer, aad a foul-mouthed ſlanderer, and a deluding perſon, by, and in <hi>Thomas Moor</hi> his Reply to <hi>James</hi> his lying Libels; thou, <hi>John Barber,</hi> haſt made thy giddy-headed raſhneſs appear, by caſting in thy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100246:13"/> teſtimony, maliciouſly to countenance lyes to deface the truth; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by haſt proved thy ſelf to be an ignorant, raſh perſon, and a cloſe enemy to truth; thou having ſaid alſo to ſome of thy Oppoſers diſdainfully, <hi>Ho, you look for Heaven out of the chimney-top;</hi> as if there were no other Heaven, but ſuch as is in your quakers ſelf-proved wicked bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. But behold how <hi>James Nayler</hi>'s condemning Law doth laſh thee alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="discourse">
               <head>SEVENTHLY,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Sparrow,</hi> quaker, how durſt thou venture to ſay, <hi>That</hi> Thomas Moor had told forty eight lyes; whenas thou being then (by one that heard thee ſay ſo) required to prove but one lye of the forty eight, thou durſt not attempt to do that: and then the ſame man requiring thee but to name one lye of the forty eight, which thou ſaid <hi>T. M.</hi> had told; but thou couldſt not do that neither: what evil doomſe-ſpirit in thee, was that, that did render thee up to an envious backbiter. And <hi>John,</hi> why didſt thou with a lofty voice vapour, and ſay, <hi>You high-flown profeſſors, the time is coming, and now is, that you will wiſh, that there never had been any Scriptures written:</hi> or to that effect in full. VVhat now <hi>John,</hi> wouldſt thou perſwade people, that God hath ſecretly hidden deadly ſpiritual poyſon under his gracious Goſpel, publiſhed in writing? Or wouldeſt thou declare by that thy ſpeech, That God hath mentally made a ſecret-ſnaring trap of his Scriptures, to deſtroy mens ſouls and bodies for ever, as men do ſet traps in ſecret places, to deſtroy noyſome vermine? what deſperate blaſphemous poyſon is wrapped up in that thy lofty ſpeech? but it appears, that you maunder thus, becauſe the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures will not own that miſ-begotten brat of yours, a third Covenant; for the Scriptures will own but two Covenants; one of VVorks, and another of Free-grace: but you quakers have carried God's firſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of VVorks, given to <hi>Adam,</hi> into the dark behinde the cloth, and have there trickt and deckt it up with the titles of Chriſt; and then you bring out that, your diſguiſed puppet, a third Covenant, and would have the Scriptures father it; but becauſe the Scriptures do gravely and ſharply diſclaim that, (your miſ-begotten brat) then (as appears by your teneats, and words aforeſaid) you would, if you could, murder the Scriptures, and bury them in perpetual oblivion.</p>
               <p>And thus <hi>John Sparrow,</hi> being an envious backbiter, and thereby a foul-mouthed ſlanderer, and thereby a notorious lyer, and thereby an enemy to God's Scripture-truths, and thereby a traytor to mens ſouls;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100246:13"/> and refuſing the Goſpel-imputation, thou haſt deſperately thrown thy ſelf down, under not onely God's eternal condemning Law; but alſo thy brother quaker, <hi>James Nayler</hi>'s condemning ſentence aforeſaid, doth lay faſt hold on thee <hi>John,</hi> teſtifying, that thou alſo art a lyer; and ſo art of the devil, and not of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="discourse">
               <head>EIGHTHLY,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anne Blaake,</hi> a principal aſpiring quaker; wherefore didſt thou, when thou wert with me and others of my Chriſtian Frieds, propound nothing, nor anſwer nothing by Scriptures, but onely with railing, and helliſh condemning cenſures? why didſt thou, although thou ſaidſt, that the Scriptures are true, yet affirm withal, that the Scriptures are not thy Rule? what didſt thou thereby affirm leſs then this, that thy Rule is a falſe Rule? And when I cited this place of Scripture to thee, <hi>He that believeth on him that juſtifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteouſneſs:</hi> what evil ſpirit provoked thee to anſwer wrathfully, that, <hi>that is a rotten foundation?</hi> But <hi>Anne,</hi> though that be not Chriſt, the bottom foundation, yet it is a ſtrong doctrinal foundation, that leads to build by faith on Chriſt's free-Grace: But, are the Scriptures true? ſayeſt thou; and yet are ſome of them falſe or rotten in thy judgement? True it is, That thou hadſt acknowledged that place of holy Scripture to be true and ſound Doctrine, then thou hadſt thereby granted, that you quakers muſt acknowledge, that you have ungodlineſs in you, or elſe your faith cannot be counted for righteouſneſs: but the devil taught thee to evade that to preſerve your falſly ſuppoſed inherent perfection, which by that Scripture is a deluſion.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Anne,</hi> thou didſt then and there ſay, That thou art the Judge of the world: not <hi>a</hi> judge, or <hi>one</hi> judge of the world, amongſt other judges; but thy luciferian ſpirit elevates thee to affirm, That thou art <hi>the</hi> judge of the world: ſo thou excluding not onely all other Saints, but alſo Chriſt himſelf, out of that thy Throne of judgement. And <hi>George Fox</hi> doth alſo ſay, That he is <hi>the</hi> judge of the world: ſo, if you were not both lyers, yet one of you muſt needs be a great lyer: and thy raging boaſting behaviour was ſuch amongſt us, that ſome did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That if ever they did ſee the devil acting in any perſon, that he was acting in thee, <hi>Anne.</hi> And that thy ſaying, not that thou ſhalt be, but <hi>that thou art the judge of the world,</hi> is another loud lye: for no Saint can be <hi>a</hi> judge of the world, much leſs <hi>the</hi> judge of the world, at any time, during this their life of their mortality.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:100246:14"/>
               <p>Thus by thy palpable luciferain pride, and notorious lyes; and by thy denying of a fundamental Doctrine of mens ſalvation, denying the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-imputation: thou, <hi>Anne Blaake</hi> haſt not onely pulled the everlaſting judgements of God's Law upon thee; but alſo thy brother quaker, <hi>James Nayler</hi>'s condemning Law aforeſaid catches faſt hold on thee, manifeſting, that thou alſo, <hi>Anne Blaake,</hi> art a lyer, and abides not in the truth, but art of the devil, and not of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="discourse">
               <head>NINTHLY,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Fox,</hi> an ancient teaching quaker. I finde, that thou <hi>George,</hi> doſt not onely pervert the Scripture to deſtructive ends, but alſo doſt falſifie the very letter of the holy Scripture, to ſupport thy deluding quakery: for I finde in a quakiſh book, called, <hi>A brief Diſcovery of a threefold eſtate of Antichriſt,</hi> in <hi>pag.</hi> 14. that <hi>George Fox</hi> doth (agreeable to the other quakers, luciferian-like) affirm, <hi>That he that ſanctifieth, and he that is ſanctified, is one:</hi> he ſaith not, they are both <hi>of one,</hi> but, <hi>is one:</hi> but the Scripture ſaith not ſo, but to the contrary: that ſaith, <hi>For both he that ſanctifieth, and they that are ſanctified, are both of one,</hi> Heb. 2.11. which is, they are all of one God, or have their being from one God acceptably, but are not one God, as <hi>George Fox</hi> falſly ſaith in full effect. True it is, That the Saints ſhall be one with God and Chriſt, in a loving acceptation on both ſides, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting glorious community, which is in full effect affirmed in <hi>John</hi> 17.21, 22, 23. but not one God in equality, but <hi>they ſhall behold his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> verſ. 24. and they being perfect in the mutual conjunction of love with him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 26. they ſhall everlaſtingly partake of his glory, which is the chief ſcope of that whole chapter, <hi>John</hi> 17. yet not in equality one God; for God ſaith in a ſharp reproof againſt ſuch luciferian aſpirers, as <hi>George Fox</hi> and the quakers prove themſelves to be, ſaying, <hi>I am the Lord, that is my Name, and my glory will I not give to another,</hi> Iſa. 42.8. though the Creature-Saints ſhall be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers in the Creators glory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in Creature-meaſure. But <hi>George Fox,</hi> affirmed and avowed, he was equal with God; as I finde recorded in print: and to back his luciferianſhip, he is charged, That he profeſſeth himſelf to be <hi>the</hi> jugde of the world; not <hi>a</hi> judge, but <hi>the</hi> judge. But <hi>Anne Blaake</hi> ſaith, ſhe is <hi>the</hi> judge of the world. And the Scripture proveth them both to be aſpiring lyers: for that doth not ſay, That the Saints are judges of the world in this their life of mortality: but that ſaith in the future tenſe, <hi>The Saints ſhall judge the world.</hi> But <hi>George
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100246:14"/> Fox</hi> more fully to declare his equality with God, if not his ſuperiority, he is charged in <hi>Saul's Errand,</hi> pag. 7. That he ſaid, he was <hi>the way, the truth, the life.</hi> But <hi>George,</hi> know thou, That he that ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and he that is ſanctified, is no otherwiſe one ſpirit, but in that myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manner, as the man and his wiſe are one fleſh, according to <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.31, 32. neither are they any otherways of his fleſh, and of his bones, <hi>verſ.</hi> 30, and 31. compared: the man and his wife remaining two diſtinct perſons ſtill: and the wife is commanded to be in ſubjection to her own husband, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1. but thy pretended equality, deſtroys thy ſubjection to thy Sanctifier.</p>
               <p>But more fully to prove his luciferianſhip, <hi>George Fox</hi> in the 8 <hi>pag.</hi> of <hi>Saul's Errand,</hi> affirmeth, That <hi>he that hath the ſame ſpirit that raiſed up Jeſus Chriſt, is equal with God; and the Saints have the ſame ſpirit in meaſure; for God's Spirit is but one:</hi> and <hi>George Fox</hi> ſaith, in the 11 <hi>pag.</hi> That he is a Saint. Thus he would again prove, That he, a poor wicked Creature, is equal with God the Creator; and if ſo, then <hi>George Fox</hi> is the Creator of <hi>George Fox,</hi> and the whole world: and he intimately claimeth Chriſt's equality with God, by his perverted citing of <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 7.</p>
               <p>But doubtleſs, thou canſt not be ignorant <hi>George,</hi> how the devil over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered <hi>John Gilpin,</hi> to proclaim in the open ſtreet, he ſaying, <hi>I am the way, the truth, and the life.</hi> And how he ſaid in full effect That he was Chriſt. And <hi>James Milner</hi> hath proved himſelf to be a falſe Chriſt. So that by theſe mad frantick paſſages, you quakers appear much like <hi>William Hacket,</hi> who in the yeer, 1541. eauſed himſelf to be proclaimed in <hi>London</hi>-ſtreets, to be Jeſus Chriſt, came with his Fan in his hand to judge the world: and he pretended, that no body could kill him; but they hanged him to death on a Gibbet in <hi>Cheap-ſide:</hi> he uttering horrible blaſphemies againſt the Majeſty of God. See Mr. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Clark</hi>'s book, intituled, <hi>A Mirror, or Looking-glaſs,</hi> pag. 225. printed, 1654.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>George Fox,</hi> becauſe of thy perſonal facts of notorious lying, falſifying and perverting of holy Scripture; and by thy luciferian pride in all theſe: thou ſhewing thy ſelf to be an enemy to God and his Truths, and to mens ſouls; and by thy deſperately refuſing the gracious relief of the Goſpel-imputation, thou <hi>George Fox</hi> alſo, art not onely condemned by God's Law, but alſo thy brother quaker, <hi>James Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi>'s law aforeſaid, adjudges thee that thou art a lyer, and ſo abides not in the truth, but art of the devil, and not of Chriſt. And it yet more manifeſtly appears, That thou, <hi>George Fox</hi> art of the devil, and not of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100246:15"/> Chriſt, becauſe, though God inſpiredly ſaith in Scriptures, <hi>For</hi> (not onely ſome, but) <hi>all Scriptures are given by inſpiration,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.16. and that ſaith, Thar even the Saints themſelves are not God's Sons any other wayes, <hi>but by adoption onely by Chriſt,</hi> (note that you quakers) not as being Chriſt, as you fooliſhly fancy; but <hi>by Chriſt:</hi> for it's written, <hi>Having predeſtinated us unto the adoption of children by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Epheſ. 1.5. ſee this confirmed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23.</p>
               <p>And Creature-adopted Sons cannot be equal with their heavenly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created Father, who vouchſafeth by free-Grace by, and in, his Son Chriſt to adopt them to be his Sons in acceptation onely. Neither can any Creature-adopted Sons, be equal with God's onely begotten Son, the Creator of all adopted Sons, and all other things, both in Heaven and in Earth alſo: therefore by thy making no reſerve or diſtinction in thy pretended equality with God, ſheweth againſt all contradiction, that thy brother quaker, <hi>James Nayler,</hi> is not miſtaken in the leaſt meaſure in his condemning cenſure aforeſaid, to adjudge all ſuch Luciferians, as thou, <hi>George Fox,</hi> haſt proved thy ſelf to be, that you are all ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and not abiders in the Truth; but are all of the devil, and not of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="discourse">
               <head>TENTHLY,</head>
               <p>I ſhall direct my pen to ſpeak with <hi>George Fox</hi> again, and <hi>Francis Hougill, Edward Burroughs, Alexander Parker, Thomas Aldam, Anthony Peirſon, Gervice Benſon, Thomas Rawlinſon, Robert Rich,</hi> and <hi>Robert Dring.</hi> Theſe ten principal quakers, in a book intituled, <hi>A Declaration againſt all Popery and Popiſh Points:</hi> they thereto appeal to the preſence of the living God of Heaven and Earth: and in their 5 and 6 <hi>pag.</hi> they do affirm, That they, and every of them alſo, do believe and know, that Salvation cannot be merited by Works; and all Doctrines in affirmation of the ſaid Points, they, and every of them, we do renounce and bear witneſs againſt; and do deny all equivocation, mental reſervation, and ſecret evaſion whatſoever: ſpeaking the words of Truth in plainneſs by the help of God. Theſe be their words. And now I ſhall make trial by their Doctrines, whether theſe ten quakers be not ſuch diſſembling Hypocrites, as <hi>James Nayler,</hi> their brother quaker, hath ſhewed himſelf to be, yea or no. To which end, we are duly to obſerve,</p>
               <p>That <hi>George Fox</hi> (their fore-man) being asked, as appears, <hi>pag.</hi> 12.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100246:15"/> of <hi>Saul's Errand,</hi> whether a believer were juſtified by Chriſt's righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs imputed; yea, or no. He anſwered, ſaying, <hi>Every beliver is born of God; and he that is born of God, is juſtified by Chriſt alone, without imputation.</hi> Theſe be his words. And hereby <hi>George Fox</hi> their fore-man, to make ſure work in this query, againſt themſelves, hath utterly refuſed all, or any imputation of Chriſt's righteouſneſs to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the quakers for their juſtification, even all Goſpel-imputation of Chriſt's righteouſneſs to them; whether Chriſt's perſon be in them, as they falſly ſay he is in them, God and Man; or that Chriſt's perſon be without them, as in truth it is: all's one with them in this great Point of mens ſalvation: for <hi>Gerge Fox</hi> their fore-man hath made no reſerve, but hath deſperately refuſed all or any imputation of Chriſt's righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to them in general.</p>
               <p>And as he (in the behalf of the quakers) hath totally refuſed the help of God's gracious Goſpel; ſo he, and the other nine quakers afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named, have together totally renounced and denied all meritorious work for mens ſalvation, and ſo they have refuſed the help of the Law alſo.</p>
               <p>But now ſee beloved, what their own great writing, teaching-brother quaker <hi>(James Parnel)</hi> doth affirm, to prove all thoſe ten quakers to be diſſembling equivocating hypocrites a for he ſhrinks not to lay forth the true Grounds of quakery without any equivocation, in his 2 <hi>page</hi> of his book, called, <hi>A Shield of the Truth:</hi> he (in the behalf of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and all quakers) there ſaying, <hi>We</hi> (to wit, we quakers) <hi>deſire to be judged according to our fruits:</hi> which is no leſs then if he had ſaid, We quakers deſire to be judged according to our own meritorious works or fruits.</p>
               <p>But yet, whatever thus appears to be in the mental boſome-reſerves of the aforeſaid ten quakers; to which (but for brevity ſake) I could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the teſtimony of more quakers; yet the aforeſaid ten quakers have deſparately refuſed and caſt away from their uſe, not onely all Goſpel-imputation of Chriſt's righteouſneſs in general, whether Chriſt's perſon be in them or without them; but alſo all legal meritorious words, as being no wayes helpful to them for their ſalvation, And hereby they have ſtrongly barred themſelves quite out, from injoying any benefit from God for their ſalvation either by his Law or Goſpel: for they have totally denied all God's revealed and eſtabliſhed wayes, which he did propound legally to <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall, or hath at any time ſince his fall, declared by his Goſpel for the ſalvation of men; and though God hath declared no other way, but one of theſe two ways for mens ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100246:16"/> yet the quakers, have as is afore ſhewed, deſperately ſhut themſelves quite out from injoying any benefit from God by any of them both; and yet doubtleſs, the quakers do deludedly conceit, That they ſhall be ſaved.</p>
               <p>Therefore in purſute, (for the diſcovery of the depths of Satan in the quakers myſtery of iniquity) I am now put to ſearch out what that hidden ſecret way is, in which the quakers do confide for their ſalvation: but I need not ſearch much, becauſe I do ſee it appear, that every quaker muſt be enabled to account and eſteem of their particular perſon, to be Chriſt; or elſe for the cauſes aforeſaid, they cannot enjoy the leaſt right quakiſh hope of Salvation: I ſay again, and ſhall ſtand to maintain it ſo long as God gives ſtrength, That if any quaker be not enabled by their grandſire <hi>Daemon,</hi> to eſteem and account of their own particular perſons to be Chriſt, who needeth not any imputation of righteouſneſs, nor any meritorious works to be applied or added to his holy, eternal, eſſential, perfect, divine perfection, that ſo long as they are not ſo ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to eſteem of their particular perſons to be Chriſt, they cannot have the leaſt right quakiſh hope to ſtrengthen them to conclude they ſhall be ſaved: but to obtain in themſelves this quakiſh comfort, it is evident, that they do declare themſelves to be Chriſt, totally without ſin as Chriſt is: for ſo they plainly ſay, <hi>As he is, ſo are we in this world:</hi> ſatani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally perverting that Scripture, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.17. for that doth not ſay, As Chriſt is in his glorified perſon in heaven without ſin, ſo are we in this world; but it ſignifieth to us, That as Chriſt is deſpiſed of many in this world, and his Doctrine refuſed, and by many contemned in this world, and eſpecially by the quakers; that ſo his ſervants are by many deſpiſed, and Doctrines contemned by many in this world, and eſpecially by the quakers in this Chriſtian world: but the quakers from that place of Scripture, ſoar up with their Antichriſtian wings, and affirm, That they are without ſin in them, as ſome of them have ſaid of themſelves in my hearing: and from hence they conclude they are Chriſt, that needeth neither imputation of righteouſneſs, nor meritorious works to be added to them: and from this ground conceited, they alſo utterly refuſe both thoſe helps, both of Goſpel and Law alſo, which is afore firmly proved from their own mouths: and to ſay, as the Truth is, they to uphold their ſelf-Chriſted indignity, muſt upon urgent neceſſity do ſo; for if they imbrace to them, (as needful for their ſalvation) the Goſpel-imputation of righteouſneſs, and meritorious works by the Law, or either of them both, then they do deſtroy totally their ſelf-conſtituted, perfect, holy Chriſthood, by their thereby acknowledging, that they have ſin in them,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100246:16"/> that do ſtand in need of thoſe additional helps for their Salvation; and then drops not onely their ſelf-advanced Chriſthoods, but alſo therewith the devils whole kingdom of quakery, is thereby totally deſtroyed root and branch: for ſome of the quakers have ſaid in my hearing, That if any man have not attained to a full perfection from all ſin in him before his death, that that man hath loſt all his labour in his ſtriving againſt ſin.</p>
               <p>And as for your quakers ſatanical evaſion, where you affirm, <hi>That though ſome of the ſervants of God fell, yet by their confeſſing and forſaking their ſin, they found mercy.</hi> Theſe are your quakiſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming words. And hereby your deceitful Tutor hath given you the ſlip again, and hath enforced your own tongues to betray you again, and to publiſh your own perpetual ſhame; for by that your ſaying, you do acknowledge in full effect with <hi>James Parnel,</hi> your brother quaker a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, That your own confeſſing and forſaking your ſins, (if you did ſo) are and can be no other, but your own meritorious works or fruits, meriting and deſerving mercy; for you ſaid, <hi>That by their confeſſing and forſaking their ſin, they found mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus you again tender up the aforenamed ten principal quakers to be diſſembling equivocating hypocrits, by your affirming (as being ing quakers) That ſalvation cannot be merited by works: but the devil leaves you not here neither; but by that your affirmation, he hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced you quakers, moſt ſhamefully to pervert that inſpired holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.13, for you over-ſtare <hi>Solomon</hi>'s ground firſt laid; for that his affirmation, he firſt teaching men how to honour God in a right manner, ſaying, <hi>Honour the Lord thy God with thy ſubſtance, and with the firſt fruits of thine encreaſe,</hi> Prov. 3.9. hereby letting us know, That God is not honoured, except a man do firſt perform his Goſpel-duties, by God, at that time, eſtabliſhed, by mens obediently of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering up to him typical ſacrifices and oblations, out of mens ſubſtance and firſt fruits of their encreaſe, then typifying Chriſt to be ſacrificed and his blood to be ſhed. And it appears, that if men then did not at firſt, not only confeſs, but alſo forſake their ſupreme ſin againſt the Goſpel of Grace, and then obediently offer up to God in the very manner by him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, ſacrifices, oblations, and offerings; then typifying Chriſt to be offered up to God his Father, and to be ſacrificed for mens ſins, that that man neglecting that Goſpel-duty, was to be cut off from amongſt his people, according to <hi>Lev.</hi> 17.8 9. and they were alſo to bear their iniquity ſtill, <hi>Lev.</hi> 7.18. whatſoever their confeſſing and forſaking their other legal ſins were.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:100246:17"/>
               <p>And thus is proved, that you quakers by your refuſing the Goſpel-imputation of the vertues of Chriſt lifted up, and ſacrificed without you for your ſins, as thoſe typical ſacrifices, and <hi>Moſes</hi> typically lifting up the brazen Serpent in the wilderneſs, were all performed without men for mens healing.</p>
               <p>And by your wilful perſiſting in the ſupreme Goſpel-ſin aforeſaid, you quakers confiding in your own meritorious confeſſing and forſaking your ſin, if in truth you do ſo, (as in truth you do not) yet even by that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, you have cut your ſelves off from amongſt God's people, and whatſoeuer you fantaſtically fancy to the contrary, you do bear your ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities ſtill, even in your own ſelf-Chriſted condition; and by Scripture, all legal exhortations in Scripture, are to be ſubjected under the aforeſaid ſupreme Goſpel-ſence: for without mens confiding in the Goſpel-Faith in Chriſt's blood ſhed, all the quakers-Chriſts and all the quakers, or any other man's Reformation, is in Gods ſight no other but noyſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; for God himſelf inſpiredly tells us plainly, That <hi>without ſhedding of blood is no remiſſion,</hi> Heb. 9.22. you quakers. And you quakers ſay, That your man Chriſt in you is ſpiritual; and a Spirit can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not die, nor have his blood ſhed: as when our Saviour's perſon was ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituallized in, by, and at his Reſurrection, it was impoſſible for him to die or have his blood to be ſhed again, ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.9. the vertues of which his blood ſhed, you having deſperately refuſed for your juſtification, you having made it appear, That your ſuppoſed Man Chriſt in you, cannot poſſibly have his blood ſhed in you for your ſins acted by you, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and more preſumptiouſly now, in your ſelf Chriſted-quakery; ſo that you have neither the vertues of Chriſt's real bloodſhed without you, nor within you to appear for your juſtification; and therefore you cannot poſſibly confide in the vertues of any blood ſhed.</p>
               <p>And thus you have again firmly ſtaked down your luciferian Chriſts to be juſtified only by your own Popiſh works, in your own confeſſing your legal ſins, and your ſuppoſed meritorious forſaking them; and thereby you have rendred up again, the forenamed ten quakers to be diſſembling, equivocating hypocrites: for behold you quakers, if you have but one corner of a ſeeing eye left you to look out of your ſelves by, what God inſpiredly ſaith in his Scriptures, (which you frequently acknowledge are true) ſee, I ſay, how highly God doth by them advance Chriſt's death and bloodſhed, and doth totally exclude works, whether wrought by men, or by any ſpirit in men whatſoever, for mens juſtification in <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24, 25. Or ſecondly, for the forgiveneſs of mens ſins <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7. Or thirdly, for the doctrinal foundation of mens faith: ſee <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8. Or
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100246:17"/> fourthly, for mens reconciliation to God: ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.19. Or fifthly, for mens Redemption: ſee <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13. Or ſixthy, for the onely way for mens encouragement, to enter by Faith, even into the holy place before God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19. All which places, and very many more ſuch, are faſtned to mens faith in Chriſt's death, and blood ſhed without men; and they are all confirmed by that grand Scripture-principle, That <hi>without ſhedding of blood is no remiſſion,</hi> Heb. 9.22. and works are totally excluded. Blood is blood, you qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers; and works are works: but they are not Chriſt's is blood. And yet you high-flown quaking Chriſts are ſo ſtifned in impudency, that you are not aſhamed to eſtabliſh your Chriſted indignity by popiſh me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious works; and yet deſperately to face it out, and in full effect cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the living God of heaven and earth to teſtifie for you, that you mean no ſuch matter.</p>
               <p>But know, you quakers, That though it is written; <hi>Work out your own ſalvation,</hi> Phil. 2.12. yet the Apoſtle in the very next Chapter ſheweth how they ſhould work that out; he telling them, that <hi>they were to (work,</hi> or) <hi>ſtrive for the Faith of the Goſpel,</hi> Phil. 1.27. <hi>through Faith in Chriſt's blood,</hi> Rom. 3.25. <hi>but not of works,</hi> Epheſ. 2.8.</p>
               <p>And beloved the quakers choice principle being, That every believer is juſtified by Chriſt alone, without Imputation. There is in this alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, That as Chriſt himſelf hath authority to execute judgement, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is <hi>the Son of man,</hi> John 5.27. and ſo <hi>hath power to forgive ſins on earth,</hi> Matth. 9.6. that ſo every quaker, Chriſt, man, or woman, muſt upon neceſſity conclude, that they have authority to judge and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie their own particular perſons, to be as free from all ſin in them, as Chriſt himſelf is; and thereby they juſtifie themſelves to be Chriſt: for they refuſe any Chriſt to be without them, to judge and juſtifie them.</p>
               <p>And thus that dark ſpeech aforeſaid comes forth cleered, ſhewing how, and by what authority every believer (to wit) every believing quaker, do juſtifie themſelves; and ſo every ſuch believer, is juſtified by a ſelf-qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker-Chriſt alone, without any imputation; which being done, then there is a quakers ſelf-conſtituted Chriſt, holy and perfect in all reſpects, inherently, without any additional imputation of any others righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to their imagined perfect perfection.</p>
               <p>And thus they make themſelves to be bran-new coyned, gliſtering Chriſts, without meritorious works alſo: for they new being Chriſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to themſelves authority to juſtifie their own Chriſthoods, without
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100246:18"/> merit or forgiveneſs from any God or Chriſt, without or beſides their own, now Chriſtes, ſelves. And further to confirm all this, they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That Chriſt had no Body but his Church, which is ſhewed in my next Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>And now to ſhew that their own actions and words, do confirm all this to be true, which hath been ſaid of them, obſerve that they, the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers (though ſome of them being not yet ripe quakers) are ſomething mealy mouthed; yet that there are many bold-faced quakers, that ſpeak out, and declare openly, ſaying, <hi>I am the way, the truth and the life; I am the judge of the world; I am equal with God; I am God's fellow; I am God.</hi> And as I have ſhewed, That divers quakers have been upon evidence charged, that they have thus ſpoken openly in full effect:</p>
               <p>So, I ſhall, paſſing by <hi>James Milner,</hi> and <hi>John Gilpin,</hi> while he was a quaker, though all their ſayings are no leſs, then if they did ſay, I am Chriſt; yet now I will, for brevity ſake onely, produce one quaker from amongſt the reſt, that did very lately proclaim openly, in divers place in <hi>Cambridge</hi>-Market, upon a Market-day; which Town is about 3 miles from me: the quaker then and there declared publickly with a loud voice, ſaying, <hi>I am Chriſt; take my yoke upon you: learn of me for I am meek and lowly of heart.</hi> The quaker taking up Chriſt's own words by him ſpoken, as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. and by that quakers ſaying directly, <hi>I am Chriſt,</hi> it being ſuitable to the other quakers affirmations, it appears there are many quaker-Chriſts: and how they come to be ſo in their own eſtimation, is before herein laid open, even to publick view; Some of them having alſo undertaken to ſave ſouls, as Chriſt did.</p>
               <p>And now it is worthy to be treaſured up in the memory of all honeſt hearts, how agreeable all theſe, the quakers publick behaviours and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations are, to our Saviour's loving forewarning by him given, and left to the world, for men to take heed of ſuch deceivers, which he then ſaid ſhould ariſe in the world, where he ſaith, <hi>Let no man deceive you; for many ſhall come in my Name, ſaying,</hi> (as it is proved they ſay) <hi>I am Chriſt,</hi> (thoſe being the very ſame words which theſe deceivers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to themſelves) <hi>and ſhall deceive many,</hi> Matth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.4, 5.</p>
               <p>And further to prove that the quakers are deceivers, note, that they ſay they have no ſin in them: and they ſay alſo by their tenents, That a man muſt be totally perfect from all ſin in him, or elſe he cannot be ſaved. But now behold how flat contrary, and againſt the Scriptures, theſe their ſayings are, where it is ſaid, <hi>There is no man that ſinneth not,</hi> 1 Kings 8.46. <hi>There is no man that ſinneth not,</hi> 2 Chron. 6.26. and that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100246:18"/> 
                  <hi>there is not a juſt man upon the earth, that doeth good, and ſinneth not,</hi> Eccleſ. 7.20. I could produce many other Teſtimonies from the Saints words; they frequently confeſſing they were ſinners: but if we will believe God's own inſpired Word, before we give credence to ſuch luciferian, and as we have before proved, diſſembling, equivocating hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites falſifiers of Scripture-words, and notorious lying quakers, then ſhall we apparently know, That they are the very ſame deceivers which our Saviour forewarns us to take heed of: for he ſaith, <hi>they ſhall deceive many;</hi> and accordingly it is very evident, that they do deceive many. And our Saviour goeth on, and ſaith, <hi>Then if any man ſay to you, Lo here is Chriſt,</hi> (as they ſay, I am Chriſt) <hi>or, lo, he is there; believe it not: for falſe Chriſts ſhall ariſe and falſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew ſigns and wonders, to deceive (if it were poſsible) the very elect; but take ye heed, behold I have ſhewed you all things before,</hi> Mar. 13.21, 22, 23.</p>
               <p>Now the quakers many Chriſts, being proved by holy Scripture to be falſe Chriſts, let us apply to that truth, the quakers proving themſelves to be falſe Prophets alſo, which is proved in my third Diſcourſe; and their ſtriving to be accounted the Prophets of the Lord, which appears in my thirteenth Diſcourſe: and adding thereto their Scripture-condemning ſigns and wonders, which are ſhewed at the quakers meetings and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which is ſhewed by complaints made againſt them, related in a printed book, called, <hi>Saul's Errand:</hi> thoſe tormenting ſigns and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, being acted upon the bodies not onely of elder people, but alſo upon, and in the bodies of little children, which the quakers do not deny. And conſidering, their aſtoniſhing ſigns and wonders ſhewed at their meeting, which appears in my fourteenth Diſcourſe. Theſe things being viewed together, it will appear cleerly, That all thoſe three marks by which our Saviour diſcovers theſe deceivers he ſpeaks of, that is to ſay, Falſe Chriſts: ſecondly, falſe Prophets: thirdly, ſhewing ſigns and wonders: are all firmly fixed by the quakers behaviours upon themſelves, That they are falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, ſhewing deceitful ſigns and wonders.</p>
               <p>And now if we do take notice in <hi>John Gilpin</hi>'s printed book, before named in my third Diſcourſe, That he therein affirmeth, that the Devil did declare to him, <hi>John Gilpin,</hi> when he was a quaker in divers ſorts of diſcoveries confirmed by a voice in him that he the devil, was Chriſt in him; and how that when the Devil did finde that <hi>John Gilpin</hi> did diſtruſt it was he ſpake in him and not Chriſt, as that voice in him pretended; and that thereupon <hi>John Gilpin</hi> declined from the Devil and the quakers,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100246:19"/> that then the Devil to draw <hi>John Gilpin</hi> into utter deſparation on the other hand, did acknowledge plainly, that he was the Devil that had taught him; and that he had been ſerving him, the Devil, and not Chriſt: and that the Devil did tell him in full effect therewith, that now it was too late for him to repent, there was no mercy for him. But <hi>John Gilpin</hi> in that book giveth God thanks for his great mercy, in delivering him from the Devil and quakery.</p>
               <p>And thus we have the Devils own teſtimony That it was he, the Devil, and not Chriſt that ſo powerfully acted in <hi>John Gilpin,</hi> whilſt he was a quaker. And ſo in this diſcovery we have the Devils own teſtimony againſt the quakers.</p>
               <p>Again, calling to minde that <hi>James Nayler,</hi> a principal teaching quaker, hath ſo firmly proved by his own behaviour, and divers other quakers; and thereby hath adjudged himſelf, and them alſo, to be lyers, and ſo not abiders in the truth, and ſo are of the Devil, and not of Chriſt: by this we have the quakers own confeſſion, condemning themſelves alſo.</p>
               <p>So that now we have, firſt, Chriſt's own teſtimony pointed forth by three ſeveral marks: ſecondly, the conſent of the Scriptures: thirdly, the quakers own confeſſion and ſelf-adjudgment: and fourthly, the teſtimony of the devil himſelf, enforced (as is before ſhewed) to ſpeak the truth: That in truth the quakers are of the very ſame many falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, ſhewing ſigns and wonders: for, ſetting the quakers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, where is to be found in all the whole world any people profeſſing Chriſtianity, as the quakers in a falſe way do, that do declare themſelves to be Chriſt, and do apply to themſelves Chriſt's titles, and do take upon them to ſave ſouls, and do declare themſelves to be Prophets, and do ſhow ſigns and wonders, as the quakers and no other people beſides them in the whole Chriſtian world do. All which, as it confirmeth the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers cenſure, That the quakers are of the Devil, and not of Chriſt; ſo is further ſtill diſcovered, that the ten forenamed quakers are lying, diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, equivocating deluding hypocrites. And I will add nothing to their own begotten titles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="discourse">
               <head>ELEVENTHLY,</head>
               <p>I ſay to thee, <hi>Leonard Fell,</hi> That whereas thou art charged in the 9 <hi>pag.</hi> of <hi>Saul's Errand,</hi> that thou <hi>Leonard Fell,</hi> didſt ſay, That Chriſt had no Body but his Church; and thou owneſt thoſe words to be thy words, by thy thereto ſtifly endeavouring to prove thoſe ſame words to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100246:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> be true: and rather then fail, thou haſt wickedly falſified the very words of holy Scripture, to prove, that thy falſe, ſaying to be true: for where the Scripture ſaith, <hi>God was in Chriſt, reconciling the world unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; not imputing their treſpaſſes unto them,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.19. and though thou citeſt that place for thy proof, yet thy deluding Tutor hath overcome thee to maintain his falſe quakery, to render that place to be thus: Thou having firſt ſaid, Chriſt came to redeem his Church, which is a truth: and as the Devil doth ſometime ſay the truth, the more eaſily thereby to deceive, even ſo thou doſt, <hi>Leonard:</hi> for cloſely following that truth, thou traileſt in thy falſhood; affirming, That God was in Chriſt, reconciling the world to himſelf for his body ſake, which is his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> And thus as if thy fingers were lime-twigs, thou haſt dragged theſe true words <hi>(not imputing their treſpaſſes to them)</hi> out of that place, which words concern the world: and then thou haſt <hi>Daemon</hi>-like craftily added unto that place, (in the room of thoſe words which thou haſt ſtollen out) theſe words, for his Bodies ſake, which is his Church; which is flat contrary to that Text: for thoſe words by thee foyſted into that place, concerns his Church onely; but the Text concerns the world. But had Chriſt no Body but his Church? ſayſt thou, <hi>Leonard.</hi> Why <hi>Leonard,</hi> you quakers ſay, That Chriſt is in your bodies, God and Man? Now <hi>Leonard,</hi> hath Chriſt (as you ſay he is Man in you) no Body of his own in you, but your bodies? how can he then poſſibly be Chriſt-Man in you, or within your bodies?</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Leonard,</hi> you quakers do frequently acknowledge both in writings and verbal words, That Chriſt did perſonally at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> though you ſay, as Chriſt-fleſh is without men, he is their example one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. But had Chriſt no Body but his Church, when he died at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> then, if that ſaying of yours were true, That Chriſt had no Body but his Church, it could be no other, but that his Church (being his onely Body) was ſlain, and put to death on the croſs at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Fie, fie, you quakers, when will you leave off your ridiculous fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</p>
               <p>But note my beloved, that by their ſaying, That they have Chriſt, God and man in them: and by their ſaying, That Chriſt had no Body but his Church: which is no other but this, That Chriſt had no Body but his Saints bodies; for his Saints are his Church: and they ſay, That they are his Saints: and every ripe quaker doth ſay, That Chriſt is in them; as their tenents do declare. Now theſe their ſayings being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared together, doth make manifeſt, That every ripe quaker in their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular bodies, are Chriſt: for they plainly affirm, That Chriſt had no
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100246:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> body but his Church, to wit, in full effect, he had no body but theirs, his Saints bodies; and ſo they would prove their own bodies to be Chriſt, or elſe Chriſt had no body at all. And this Logick of theirs doth ſo fully again diſcover that which is ſaid of them in my laſt Diſcourſe, concerning their proclaiming themſelves to be Chriſt, &amp; their attributing to themſelves Chriſts power and titles, that it is worthy of much obſervation.</p>
               <p>But know all you quakers, That God's inſpired Word, his holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, are ſo far contrary to your ſatanical enthuſemiated teachings, that they do not onely deny, that your bodies are Chriſt's body; but they alſo do deny, that Chriſt's perſon or body is in your bodies; which to your ſhame and utter confuſion, you may behold, where it is ſaid plainly by two Meſſengers (as it appears) ſent from Heaven in white apa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> which alſo ſaid <hi>Ye men of Galilee, why ſtand ye gazing up into heaven? this ſame Jeſus, which is taken up from you into heaven, ſhall ſo come in like manner, as ye have ſeen him go into heaven,</hi> Acts 1.10, 11. And this place alone is altogether ſufficient utterly to deſtroy your vainly conceited perſonal Man-Chriſt in you; and alſo to pull down your ſpacious heaven, which by your devil like perverting the holy Scripture, you beſotted quakers, do imagine to be in your ſelf-proved wicked bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; and to the very ſame end, do you a ſpiring quakers, vouchſafe to look down into theſe Scriptures, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.30. and 26.64. <hi>Mark</hi> 13.26. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4 17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.23. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Titus</hi> 3.13. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2.</p>
               <p>And alſo know all you quakers, That your betters, and better taught even of God, (though you are taught of the Devil) do ſay, <hi>The holy Ghoſt is ſent down from heaven,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.12. and that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt is gone into heaven, and is on the right hand of God,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.22. then neither God's eſſence, nor the heaven in which God's eſſence is, nor Chriſts perſon, was in <hi>Peters</hi> holy body, though your tenents brag, that all theſe are in your bodies.</p>
               <p>Again, you quakers, holy St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Our converſation is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, from whence alſo we look for the Saviour, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 3.20. then Chriſt's perſon, nor the heaven which it is in, was not in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> body. Again, you quakers, St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth yet ſtrike more fiercely at that your conceited Man-Chriſt in you, where he ſaith, <hi>Whilſt we are at home in the body, we are abſent from the Lord,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.6. and he explaineth what he means by the word <hi>body,</hi> he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it, <hi>Our earthly houſe of this tabernacle,</hi> verſ. 1. And by the bright and warm Scripture ſun-beams, your quakers Heaven, and God, and Man-Chriſt in you, are vaniſhed away into a noyſome and ſtinking
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100246:20"/> helliſh fog; and the Devil is laid open ſpeaking in thee, <hi>Leonard Fell,</hi> by thy ſaying, That Chriſt had no body but his Church: and by thy ſo <hi>Daemon</hi>-like, falſifying the words of the holy Scripture, to face out thy lyes to be as if they were truth; ſo fathering thy lyes upon God himſelf. But <hi>Leonard</hi> I will tell thee, That by thy taking out, and adding to the words, of that bock, thou haſt deſperately involved thy ſelf, not onely to have thy part taken out of the book of Life, but alſo to have all the plagues fall upon thee, <hi>Leonard,</hi> that are written in that book, as is in full effect affirmed in <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.18, 19. and not onely God's Law thus fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemns thee and all ſuch falſe quakers, as thou haſt proved thy ſelf to be, but alſo thy brother quaker <hi>James Naylers</hi> condemning Law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, doth adjudge thee <hi>Leonard Fell,</hi> by thy ſelf manifeſted evil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour to be a lyer, and ſo no abider in the truth, but art of the Devil, and not of Chriſt; and becauſe you quakers do refuſe the gracious bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Goſpel-imputation, that <hi>James Naylers</hi> cenſure of thee, <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> is true and juſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="discourse">
               <head>TWELFTHLY,</head>
               <p>My twelfth Diſcourſe is with thee <hi>Martha Simmonds:</hi> and truely <hi>Martha</hi> thy folly is ſo apparent, that I could almoſt have ſeemed to have thrown by my pen, and have left thee to have been cenſured by thine own groſs ignorance, by thee publiſhed in print: but yet I ſhall do thee this favour <hi>Martha,</hi> to help thee to ſee how the Devil deludes thee, (if it may be.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martha,</hi> I finde in thy bock, which thou calleſt, <hi>A Lamentation for the loſt Sheep;</hi> amongſt divers quakiſh errors by thee therein manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as <hi>birds of a feather will flock together,</hi> that even ſo thou <hi>Martha</hi> alſo, haſt perverted and wickedly falſified the cleer and plain ſenſe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, to ſerve thy maſter Satan, where thou ſayeſt, <hi>Now Jeſus Chriſt, the ſecond</hi> Adam, <hi>who is God manifeſted in the fleſh, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning ſin in the fleſh, if thou live in him</hi> in thee, <hi>and believe in him</hi> in thee, <hi>thou ſhalt witneſs his power to the cutting down of thy will; for thy will muſt come to death, that the will of God may be done; and ſo that Scripture comes to be fulfilled in thee, which are the words of Chriſt,</hi> Lo I come, in the volume of thy book it is written of me, to do thy will, O God: <hi>which is the book of conſcience in thee, there the will of God is to be done.</hi> Theſe be thy words, <hi>Martha.</hi> And now know thou and all quakers, That Jeſus Chriſt is before now come in his own diſtinct perſon of fleſh without men, but not come per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100246:21"/> in yours: nor any other mans body of fleſh, which is largely and firmly proved in my two laſt Diſcourſes: ſo that a man is not ſo to live in him <hi>in him,</hi> nor ſo to believe in him <hi>in him,</hi> as thou falſly ſaieſt: for you quakers, Chriſt dwells in no man any other wayes but by Faith, which is in plain and full effect proved in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. neither is Chriſt abidingly in any man, no not in God's ſons, but by his Spirit, which is alſo proved in <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. and from this ground, Chriſt's Spirit is called the Spirit of Faith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 4. and from thence the Saints are ſaid to be the habition of God through to Spirit, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.22. but not whole Chriſt, God and Man in men, but by faith and his Spirit: and therefore theſe Scriptures do confound that thy ſaying <hi>Martha.</hi> And whereas thou ſaieſt, That that Scripture, <hi>Lo I come, in the volume of thy book it is written of me, to do thy will, O God,</hi> Heb. 10.7. is to be fulfilled in men. It is ſo evident, That that will of God in that ſame Scripture men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, is already fulfilled in Chriſts perſon onely, and never was fulfilled in any other perſon, nor never can be wrought over again in Chriſts per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon neither: for that will of God was fulfilled by Chriſts death in his being ſacrificed; but Chriſt being raiſed from the dead, dieth no more, death hath no more dominion over him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.9. This again proves cleerly, That you quakers are not Chriſt as you brag you are; for Chriſt now cannot die: but it is apparent that you quakers do die, as other men do; therefore you quakers are not Chriſt: and yet you are ſo impudent, that you dare to ſay, That as Chriſt is, ſo are you in this world; but ſhame attends upon you.</p>
               <p>But to proceed, it is evident, That that will of God in that thy cited place mentioned, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.7. is not to be fulfilled in any mans perſon whatſoever, but as that will of God hath been already perfectly fulfilled in Chriſt's perſon, by his being perſonally ſacrificed without men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he did put a total end to the vertues of all, or any typical ſacrifices. And this is ſo evident a truth, flying even in the very face of that thy falſe and lying ſaying, <hi>Martha,</hi> that it would be altogether ſuperfluous any further to prove it, then to intreat my Reader to peruſe <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. from the 1 <hi>verſ.</hi> to the 12. In which ſpace, <hi>Martha's</hi> wickedly abuſed <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. is included.</p>
               <p>And again, <hi>Nartha,</hi> whereas thou ſaieſt, That by the volume of the book in that place mentioned, is meant, of the volume of the book of mens conſciences, it is evident againſt the Devil ſpeaking in thee, <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> that by the volume of the book in that place mentioned, is plainly meant to be the volume of the books of the Prophets; for the ſame words written in thy cited <hi>verſ. Heb.</hi> 10.7. <hi>Lo I come, in the volume of thy
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100246:21"/> book it is written of me</hi>) do appear plainly in the Prophet <hi>David's</hi> book, in his <hi>Pſalm</hi> 40.6, 7, 8. and in the volume of the Prophet <hi>Moſes</hi> book, and <hi>Eſay</hi> 53. and divers other Prophets, do in the volume of their books ſpeak ſo clearly of Chriſt's death, and being to be ſacrificed, that it would utterly be time loſt, any further to prove againſt thy quakiſh notorious lyes, which thou haſt learned by-heart, by thy accuſtomed dancing after the Devil's pipe.</p>
               <p>And hereby appears, That by your quakers luciferian-like bragging, as if you onely were in the light; and yet by your falling down ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely ſhort in the underſtandings of ſuch cleer and plain places of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and by your delivering ſuch eternally deſtructive Doctrine from them, you deliver up your ſelves to be one of the moſt deluded and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding miracles and monſters of the whole world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="discourse">
               <head>THIRTEENTHLY,</head>
               <p>My thirteenth Diſcourſe is directed to the four and twentieth quaker, the mighty writing quaker, <hi>James Parnel.</hi> And now comes his fearful blaſphemies tumbling out of his (Thraſo-like) boaſting lying book, which he calls, <hi>A Shield of the Truth:</hi> for obſerve my Reader, and though it be one or more of the ſelf-Chriſted quakers, I care not: for, as it were, paſſing by <hi>James Parnels</hi> murthering of himſelf in <hi>Colcheſter</hi>-Goal, by his inordinate (and by Scripture-condemned) faſting as he ſaid luciferian-like, to ſhew himſelf to be a Prophet of the Lord, for people to believe in him, which was not to believe his words; but to believe in him, to whom he promiſed the eternal joyes of heaven, as I finde record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſaid to be licenſed according to order. And paſſing by the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous bulk of his great quakiſh errors, his whole book being nothing elſe but lyes in the drift of it, I ſhall for brevity ſake, onely diſcover ſome few of them, to give a taſte to all the reſt: and to this end, I finde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by him in his 31 <hi>pag.</hi> he therein affirming, That <hi>John</hi> (to wit, the holy Apoſtle S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>John</hi>) though his peramount height would not ſtoop ſo low as to call him ſo; but as being his equal, if not his ſuperiour, he affirmed <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>He that hath hope in him, purifieth himſelf, even as he is pure:</hi> but St. <hi>John</hi> did not ſay ſo; for he ſaith, <hi>Every man that hath this hope in him, purifieth himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. But <hi>James Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi> hereby, not onely falſifieth the very words of Scripture, by his taking the moſt ſignificant word <hi>this</hi> out of that Text; but he alſo therewith telleth a notorious lye againſt all denial, by his affirming <hi>John</hi> ſaid ſo; and ſo he alſo fathereth his loud lye upon St. <hi>John,</hi> by his affirming <hi>John</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:100246:22"/> ſaid ſo, <hi>He that hath hope in him;</hi> whereas St. <hi>John</hi> ſaid not ſo; but ſaid, <hi>Every man that hath this hope in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But beloved, it is worth our ſearch to futer out the cauſe why <hi>James Parnel</hi> was ſo frighted, as to take out of that Text that ſignificant word <hi>this:</hi> and we ſhall finde, that if <hi>James Parnel</hi> had not taken out the word <hi>this,</hi> it would have led his Reader to ſearch further to know what is meant by <hi>this hope,</hi> as diſtinct from all other hopes; and his Reader would finde out in the very next <hi>verſe</hi> going before that <hi>verſe,</hi> what St. <hi>John</hi> meant by his ſaying, <hi>Every man that hath this hope:</hi> for St. <hi>John</hi> in his very next precedent <hi>verſe,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Behold, now are we the Sons of God, and it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be; but we know, that when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is,</hi> 1 John 3.2. but then in the next <hi>verſe</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>And every man that hath this hope in him, purifieth himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. to wit, that hope which St. <hi>John</hi> declareth in his 3 <hi>verſe.</hi> But <hi>James Parnel</hi> was ſo amazed at thoſe words, <hi>this hope,</hi> that he craftily took that word <hi>this</hi> out of that Text, before he could make any quakiſh Doctrine of it. But why ſo? why ſo? ſay you. Why, if he had taken in thoſe words <hi>this hope,</hi> they would have diſcovered,</p>
               <p>Firſt, That whereas the quakers ſay, That Chriſt's appearing the ſecond time without ſin unto ſalvation, is manifeſted and accompliſhed in them, both as Chriſt is God and Man. But even the Sons of God in that Text do cry down, that the quakers, affirmation, as being a deluſion of the Devil; for they, even the Sons of God, do affirm the flat contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſay in full effect, That <hi>Chriſt had not appeared by his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond perſonal coming, not ſo much as to them: therefore much leſs in them:</hi> though the quakers ſay, That Chriſt is in them God and Man.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Thoſe words <hi>this hope</hi> doth diſcover, that whereas the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers do affirm, That they are ſo like Chriſt, even in theſe their dayes of mortality, that they do venture audaciouſly to ſay, <hi>As he is, ſo are we in this world,</hi> even totally without ſin in them, as Chriſt is: for they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That if a man be not totally free from ſin in him he cannot be ſaved. But even the ſons of God, do even in that Text affirm againſt the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, That they were not like him in the dayes of their mortality, and ſo were not then free from all ſin in them, as Chriſt is; nor that they, though they were even the Sons of God, yet were not then ſo like Chriſt, nor ſhould be untill his ſecond perſonal appearing; for they there ſay, <hi>We know that when we ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him; and it doth not yet appear, what we ſhall be,</hi> Thus punctually, the Sons of God do by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100246:22"/> thoſe words <hi>this hope,</hi> confound that the quakers luciferian comparing themſelves in equality to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Thoſe words <hi>this hope</hi> do diſcover, that whereas the quakers tenents do maintain, that no man can be a Son of God, until Chriſt's ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond appearing God and man, be manifeſted and accompliſhed in him. But St. <hi>John,</hi> and other Sons of God, do in that Text maintain in plain and full effect, that the Saints are the Sons of God, even before Chriſts ſecond perſonal appearing to them, much leſs in them. And whereas the quakers in full effect affirm, that they have Chriſt, God and Man in them in poſſeſſion: the Sons of God do affirm by that Text, that it is their hope, that Chriſt will appear at his ſecond perſonal coming to them, and not perſonally in them in poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>And thus the holy Goſpel-truths comprehended under thoſe words, <hi>this hope,</hi> in that Text mentioned, do utterly deſtroy all the three grounds upon which the whole Doctrine of quakery is founded, even root and branch.</p>
               <p>Now was it not high time, think you my beloved, for <hi>James Parnel</hi> to flie ſwiftly away from thoſe words <hi>this hope:</hi> This hope quotha, it is enough not onely to affright <hi>James Parnel</hi> out of his light quakiſh wits, but it doth alſo confound all the quakers, not onely theſe in all <hi>England</hi> but alſo all quakers in all the whole world, although no other Scriptures, which do maintain the ſame Goſpel infallible truths, be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced againſt them: for thoſe two <hi>verſes,</hi> 1 John 3.2 3, are a key as is ſhewed, to open a door of truth, which doth utterly deſtroy all qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kery, root, ſtem, and twig, <hi>this hope</hi> quotha. I wonder <hi>James Parnal</hi> durſt venture to come ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eer it: but you may ſee beloved, That Satan in him, and with him, did go as wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ily to work as they could; for they firſt dragged that directing word <hi>this</hi> out of that Text; and then, ſo falſified, they vapouringly howl'd i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> forth, (as it were) ſaying, See here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e purity of the quakers: Behold <hi>John</hi> ſaith, That the quakers have ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me kinde of hope in them.</p>
               <p>And now note <hi>James Parnel</hi>'s direct falſifying the very words of the Scripture again: for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his 30 and 31 <hi>pag.</hi> he ſaith, <hi>He that hath ſin, and ſaith he hath no ſin, deceives himſelf, and is a lyer.</hi> Thus be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, That there are ſome me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that have no ſin in them, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th affirmed of himſelf in my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earing of which here<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded words, <hi>He that hath ſin</hi> did not in that Text, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by his taking the word <hi>this</hi> out of the Scriptures, as b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> his adding words unto the Scripture to delude people with, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved himſelf, not onely to have his part taken out of the book <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:100246:23"/> but alſo to have all thoſe plagues inflicted on him, that are written in the book, as is in full effect ſhewed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18, 19. and for his lying bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quaker, <hi>James Nayler</hi>'s condemning law, alſo adjudgeth him to be of the devil, and not of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And now to diſcover <hi>James Parnel</hi>'s notorious lyes, and fearful blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, mixt together in his quakiſh <hi>Shield of the Truth;</hi> note, That in his 29 <hi>pag.</hi> he ſaith, That it is a great deluſion of the Devil to keep people in ſin, to tell them, They ſhall never be made free from ſin, ſo long as they were upon the Earth; and brings Scripture to prove it, <hi>He that ſaith, he hath no ſin deceiveth himſelf, and is a lyer:</hi> but he (to wit, the Devil) tells them, Chriſt died for all; and if they can but lay hold on him by Faith, he will not impute their ſins unto them, though they ſin dayly: <hi>for the righteous man ſins ſeven times a day;</hi> and all the holy men of God ſinned: and he (to wit, the Devil) takes Scripture to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his Kingdom. And this he (to wit, the Devil) delivers by the mouth of his Miniſters, which he (to wit, the Devil) ſends abroad to deceive the Nations. Theſe are his words, onely thoſe within the parentheſis excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which do but lay forth his own ſenſe which any man may eaſily ſee that reads them.</p>
               <p>And now beloved note firſt, That <hi>James Parnel</hi> doth violently ſtrike at the very face of the Goſpel of Grace; for he in full effect ſaith, (that it is not onely a deluſion, but alſo) it is a great deluſion of the devil to teach men to know, that there is no man that hath no ſin in him, which Goſpel-Doctrine is maintained in plain and full effect in 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.8. and to teach men to know, That Chriſt died for all, which are the Goſpel-words of 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.13. and to tell men, That if they lay hold on Chriſt by Faith he will not impute their treſpaſſes to them, which ſaying is in plain and full effect maintained to be true Goſpel-Faith in <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.5. but <hi>James Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi> affirmeth in full effect, That to teach men to know theſe Goſpel-truths and words unaltered, is no other but a great deluſion of the Devil.</p>
               <p>Doubtleſs, ſome men do make evil of the Goſpel of Grace, by the Devils perverting of it to falſe deluding ends to them; and ſo they are led to take liberty therefrom to continue in ſin: but it appears cleerly in that his aforeſaid ſpeech, that this is not the mark which <hi>Iames Parnal</hi> ſhoots the Devils fiery darts at: for he doth not finde fault, that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and his miniſters do alter and falſifie the words of the Scripture, and then uſe the Scripture ſo altered to decieve the Nations with; but he luciferian-like, affirmeth in full effect, that it is a great deluſion of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, to teach men by and with the plain Scripture-words unaltered and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falſified,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100246:23"/> which their toad-like venome, being by them ſpat in the face of the Goſpel of Grace, appears evidently in that aforeſaid ſpeech of <hi>James Parnel</hi>'s; and the cauſe of all that their devil-like malice appears to be this, becauſe the infallible truth of the holy Goſpel of Grace, doth cry down their diabolically conceited-Chriſted Salvation, by holy legal works, wrought perfectly in mens bodies, which is largely and firmly proved by Scriptures in this Treatiſe. But the great and holy Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that Goſpel-Champion meets with them, and he draws out Chriſts word and ſword, the Scriptures; and therewith he ſtrikes off the very head of that, their imagined legal Chriſt in them, at one Goſpel-blow, where he telleth both us and them alſo, That <hi>he was ſet for the defence of the Goſpel,</hi> Phil. 1.17. and he ſaith thereto. <hi>For neceſſity is laid upon me; yea, wo is unto me, if preach not the Goſpel,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.16.</p>
               <p>Yet this their ſpite againſt the plain words of the holy Goſpel-Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, is not the height of their malice againſt Goſpel-truths: for in that their ſpeech aforeſaid, they do in full effect accuſe all the holy Saints, for their ſo freely, and fully, and truely acknowledging, that they had ſin in them, which is to be ſeen 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.20. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.46. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.36. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.2. <hi>James</hi> 3.2. <hi>James</hi> 5.17. <hi>Phil.</hi> 13.12, 13. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4, 4. and in many other places of the Scriptures: but the quakers in that their aforeſaid ſpeech ſaid in full effect, that all thoſe, and all other ſuch humble confeſſing Saints, do teach not onely a deluſion, but alſo a great deluſion of the Devil, to keep people in ſin, and to maintain the devils kingdom by their ſo humbly and faithfully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging, that they had ſin in them.</p>
               <p>But now as they do vainly alledge againſt this in their records, ſo me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I hear the quakers yelling out, and ſaying, Ho, <hi>Wade!</hi> though St. <hi>David,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul.</hi> did once complain of ſin in them, yet after that, they attained to full perfection, and then they complained no more of their ſin.</p>
               <p>But you ignorant quakers, ſee your folly in this alſo; for the Prophet <hi>David</hi> doth rebuke you, he ſaying, <hi>Enter not into judgement with thy ſervant, for in thy ſight ſhall no man living be juſtified,</hi> Pſal. 143.2. And now you quakers may ſee, that by his affirming in full, That no man living ſhall be juſtified in God's ſight; that the Prophet <hi>David</hi> doth even thereby acknowledge, as fully, that he himſelf could not either in or of himſelf in his own perſon, be any ways juſtified in God's ſight, at any time ſo long as he was a living man upon the earth: and this his humble, and faithful plain acknowledgement, doth firmly prove, even againſt all contradiction, that the Prophet <hi>David</hi> was not free from ſin
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100246:24"/> in him, at any time whilſt he live upon the earth; and therefore he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſin was in him, that made him ſo affirm, he did not ſay, Bleſſed is the man that hath no ſin nor iniquity in him; but on the contrary to that, he ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed is the man, to whom the Lord imputeth not ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, whoſe ſin is covered,</hi> Pſal. 32.1, 2. So ſin not being totally taken away, but by Goſpel-Grace, not imputed or covered under the vertues of the precious blood of Jeſus by his Goſpel-Faith in Jeſus. And thus is fully proved, that the Prophet <hi>David</hi> was never at any time free from having ſin in him at any time whilſt he was a living man upon the earth; and thereby it is fully proved, that you quakers are helliſh ſeducing lyers.</p>
               <p>And now concerning St. <hi>Paul</hi> he acknowledged that he was not free from ſin, even at the finiſhing of his courſe: for as he affirmed he had ſin in him <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. and acnowledged that he was not perfect, in <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12, 13. even ſo along he further ſaid, <hi>I am now ready to be offered, and the time of my departure is at hand: I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.5, 6.</p>
               <p>Now behold you quakers, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> did not then, even at the very finiſhing of his courſe, glory that he was free from all ſin in him: No, not one word ſo: but he rejoycing in this onely, when he had finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his courſe, that he had kept the faith in his inward man, intimating, to releive him from his ſin, that even at the finiſhing of his courſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in his outward man, or fleſh, which fully agrees to his ſaying, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.25. and he alſo ſheweth us what kinde of Faith it was, which he even at the very time of the finiſhing of his courſe onely gloried in; and that his faith was not a believing on him that juſtifieth no man but ſuch men that are free from all ſin in them, and ſo are perfectly and inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently godly men: no, not ſo neither; but on the direct contrary, he ſheweth to us, and you quakers alſo, that his ſaith was his believing on him, <hi>that juſtifieth the ungodly, whoſe faith is counted to him for righteouſneſs,</hi> Rom. 4.5. he thereby plainly declaring, that though he had ſin him in his outward man, or fleſh, even at the very time of his fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing his courſe, yet that his faith in his inward man, was even at that very time his righteouſneſs with God by Chriſt, and accordingly he even then gloried onely in this, that by his fighting a good fight, he had kept the faith, even at his finiſhing his courſe, and agreeable thereto the whole ſcope of his Goſpel is the advancing of mens faith in Chriſt's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood ſhed without them, and his totally excluding works from mens juſtification. And hereby it is firmly proved, that St, <hi>Paul</hi> was
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100246:24"/> not free from ſin in him at the very finiſhng his courſe. And as theſe two examples of St. <hi>David</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> do ſet forth the true conditions of all Saints, whilſt they are living on earth: ſo it again proveth, that you qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers are ſatanical decieving lyers.</p>
               <p>And whereas I do finde that <hi>James Nayler</hi> hath laid his foul fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of quakery upon the undefiled truth of that <hi>verſe.</hi> Rom. 4 5. I ſhall waſh off that ſoyl God willing, at ſome other time.</p>
               <p>And now to ſhew you quakers (whom I finde to be groping in the dark, the eyes of your underſtandings being darkened and dazeled with your inward great quakiſh light you boaſt of) what is the true cauſe next under the devil himſelf, your teacher, why you quakers do ſo fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickly and wildely ſtraggle quite away from the truth of the Scripture; which is, firſt, becauſe you frequently affirm, that the Scriptures are not your Rule; and truly, in this I do verily believe you, for I do finde it to be even ſo. In the ſecond place, that though God hath inſpiredly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in his Scriptures, that there is an inward and outward man in one and the ſame man in Gods account and eſtimation, yet you are trayld a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from this true Scripture-diſtinction: ſo far that by your quakiſh Doctrine you do vainly conclude, That if any man be free from the guilt of ſin in God's Goſpel-account, that that man, even upon neceſſity muſt be totally free from all tincture of the pollution of ſin in him both in his inward man or minde, and in his outward man or fleſh alſo, which is directly contrary to the Scriptures: for St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I delight in the law of God after the inward man,</hi> Rom. 7.22. which ſaying of his doth unſeperably ſet forth, that there was even at that very time an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man comprehended in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s perſon, which he calls his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. his fleſh, <hi>verſ</hi> 25. &amp; more cleerly to ſet forth his diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he further ſaith, <hi>With the minde I my ſelfe ſerve the law of God, but with the fleſh the law of ſin,</hi> verſ. 23. and he yet further cleereth this diſtinction, where he twice affirmeth, <hi>If I do that I would not, it is no more I that do it but ſin dwelleth in me,</hi> verſ. 16. and <hi>verſ</hi> 20. and it's already proved, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was not free from ſin in him, no not at the finiſhing of his courſe.</p>
               <p>And therewith he doth cleerly ſhew, That as in him, ſo in all other Goſpel-believers an inward man or ſpirit of the minde, wherewith and wherein, they ſerve the Law of God as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.25. with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out guil and hypocriſie, in their integrity; and this St. <hi>Paul</hi> owned to be in himſelf, which inward man ſo acting, is eſteemed of God to be the man, or that he which is born of God in every true Goſpel-believers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which ſinneth not, neither indeed can ſin, in that ſin which is un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100246:25"/> death, though thorow the ſtrength of temptations, working upon the infirmity of their outward man, or fleſh: there may be ſome ſin that is not unto death ſound in their perſons; all which St. <hi>John,</hi> who was born of God, yet even then acknowledgeth himſelf to be amongſt other Saints, one ſinner, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8. onely he diſtinguiſheth betwixt that ſin which is not unto death, (in which even that perſon who is born of God in his inward man, may probably through infirmity be found ſinning in his outward man) and that ſin which St. <hi>John</hi> intimates, is againſt the holy Ghoſt, which is unto death, which he that is born of God, neither doth nor can ſin, becauſe he is born of God: all which truths St. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſheweth in full effect, in 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.9. and more fully in 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.16, 17, 18. but the quakers Tutor will not permit them to ſee the Truth, But St. <hi>Paul</hi> yet further confirmeth his diſtinction aforeſaid, where he ſaith in plain and full effect, That with his outward man or fleſh, he ſerved the law of ſin, <hi>Rom</hi> 7.25. and this, his outward man, or fleſh, though it was even then a part of his own perſon, yet he owned it not to be himſelf, for he brands that his outward man, or fleſh, to be another law in his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, (fleſh, or outward man) warring againſt the law of his minde, <hi>v.</hi> 23. which his inner man or minde he owneth to be himſelf, <hi>v.</hi> 25. that ſinned not.</p>
               <p>And now behold you quakers, how amongſt others theſe three holy, and with God highly eſteemed Saint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Job, David,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, yet further confirm this Scripture-diſtinction unanimouſly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Behold, I ſay, how ſtifly, ſtoutly and boldly, that holy man <hi>Job</hi> ſtood it out, even with God himſelf, to juſtifie himſelf in his inner man, to be perfectly without guile in his integrity, he deſiring in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, ſaying, <hi>Let me be weighed in an even ballance, that God may know mine integrity,</hi> Job 31.6. and yet notwithſtanding all this height of his boldneſs to juſtifie himſelf in his inner mans perfection, in his integrity, yet he durſt not in the leaſt meaſure, ſtand to juſtifie himſelf to be free from ſin in his outward man: but on the flat contrary, he as it were mournfully ſaid, <hi>If I juſtifie my ſelf, mine own mouth will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn me; if I ſay, I am perfect, it will prove me per verſe,</hi> Job 9.20. ſee alſo the 30, and 31 <hi>verſes</hi> therein; No, no, though he ſo bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtood it out, even with God, to juſtifie the perfection of his integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his inward man; yet he, as it were cries out againſt the imperfection that was even then in his outward man: and in this reſpect, he ſoars up upon the wings of his faith, and flies quite out of himſelf to reſt in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer onely, he then ſaying, <hi>I know that my redeemer liveth,</hi> &amp;c, <hi>Iob</hi> 19.25. and even ſo, you evil taught quakers ſhould do.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:100246:25"/>
               <p>And now concerning <hi>David,</hi> behold he ſaith, <hi>Behold, thou deſireſt truth in the inward parts and in the inward part thou ſhalt make me to know wiſdom,</hi> Pſal. 51.6. And this again unſeparably ſets forth to view an outward unteachable part, to be in the ſame man, even at one and the ſame time, in Gods eſtimation. And now obſerve how boldly and ſtoutly the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſtood it out, even with God in defending and juſtifying the perfection of his integrity in his inward man, or minde, where he dares to ſay, even to God himelf, <hi>Search me O God, and know my heart; try me, and know my thoughts</hi> Pſal. 139.23. Nay, ſee how deeply he ventuers yet further, in defending the ſoundneſs of his integrity, in his inward man, where he boldly called upon God ſaying, <hi>Judge me,</hi> (note this) <hi>Judge me, O Lord; for I have walked in mine integrity,</hi> Pſal. 26.1. And now who would have thought, that this holy <hi>David</hi> would have cried, <hi>peccavi?</hi> but yet behold, notwithſtanding that his great height of boldneſs with God, to defend and juſtifie the perfection and ſoundneſs of his integrity in his inward man or minde, yet he, as it were, condemns his perſon, as having in it ſin in his outward man or fleſh, or in this reſpect he changes his tune, and now becomes an humble Sui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to God, to pardon and forgive his ſins, very often in the Pſalms; and he lamentably entreats: and though in the firſt reſpect, he boldly called upon God to judge him, yet in reſpect of his juſtifying his perſon to be free from ſin in it, he humbly entreats the Lord not to judge him, ſaying, <hi>Enter not into judgement with thy ſervant; for in thy ſight ſhall no man living be juſtified,</hi> Pſal. 143.2. then he could not be juſtified by and in himſelf at any time, whilſt he was a living man upon the earth; and this he therein confeſſeth in full effect: and yet you quakers are not aſhamed, not onely to ſay, That the Prophet <hi>David</hi> was free from ſin, or was perfect in the time when he lived upon the earth; but alſo lucife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian-like, to affirm in full effect, that you are free from ſin in you in your inward and outward man both, though theſe holy Saints acknowledge the flat contrary, which you unruly quakers ſhould alſo do.</p>
               <p>And for St. <hi>Paul,</hi> his acknowledgement is ſo large, that there is in a true Believer, an obedient inward man, and a rebellious outward man, that I ſhall need only to intreat my Reader to peruſe <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus we finde out the cauſe, why the holy Saints that are born of God do acknowledge themſelves to be ungodly, and the ground alſo from which St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth ſo highly advance his Faith that believeth on him that juſtifieth the ungodly, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 4, 5, is hereby cleerly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:100246:26"/>
               <p>And now again, if you can poſſibly wipe your quakiſh eyes to any good effect, here you may ſee God's bleſſed people: why do you ſeek the living amongſt the dead? Here, here, you quakers; here are they that keep the Commandments of God, and the Faith of Jeſus alſo, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.12. that are ſo highly commended of God therein for their ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, though you quakers keep neither of them both. Here, you quakers are they, that though they ſee that they do through the infirmity of their fleſh, break the commandments of their God in their outward man, yet they with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 7.25. do ſerve the Law of God, and ſo keep the Commandments of God in their inward man, or Spirit of their minde, and do alſo in their inward man keep the Faith of Jeſus to be juſtified thereby onely from the tranſgreſſions (that like a conquered ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious thief) ſtill remaining in their outward man continually rebelling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law of their minde or inward man. Here here, you quakers, is the patience of the Saints commended in <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.12. though your quakers aſpiring ſpirit will not ſtoop ſo low as to endure that, the Saints holy war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare upon the earth;</p>
               <p>But therefore know, all you quakers, that when St. <hi>Paul</hi> prayed thrice, that the thorne or ſin in his fleſh might depart from him, if God had taken that away from him, and ſo conſequently from all his Saints, then all they with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> had been thereby exalted above meaſure, even as it appears manifeſtly by you, that you quakers do exalt your ſelves to a Chriſthood diabollically far above meaſure, by your vainly conceiting, that the thorne or ſin in your fleſh, is totally taken from you: and not onely ſo, but God had alſo thereby deſtroyed the tranſcendent glory of of his Goſpel-free-grace, granted by his eſpecial grace to men, in, and by Chriſt for Goſpel-relief, even ever ſince <hi>Adam</hi>'s legal fall: but you may ſee, that God would not grant that, though it was a threefold hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Petition of his choice veſſel, St. <hi>Paul;</hi> but onely for his comfort God then told him, that his <hi>grace was ſufficient for him:</hi> God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with acquainting him that his ſtrength is made perfect in weakneſs: all which is ſhewed in full effect in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7, 8, 9. And thus in one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, he ſheweth us how he both preſerved St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and doth preſerve all his Saints from being exalted above meaſure, as you quakers extremely are. And alſo God by that thorne, ſin, and helpful afflictions, not taken away from the Saints, doth preſerve the glory of his Goſpel free-grace to himſelf, as moſt due is, which is even by all men heartily to be alwayes acknowledged; but you quakers whilſt being quakers, ſo exalted above meaſure, cannot poſſibly taſte of this ſweet Goſpel-cup of God's ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by him freely ſet forth in Chriſt his Son, by his death and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100246:26"/> blood ſhed, without your quakers or any other mens bodies what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
               <p>And now whatſoever the lofty ſelf-Chriſted quakers will do, or will not do, yet let us beloved, take yet further notice of the precious eſteem which God doth faſten on all ſuch people, which are free from guile and hypocriſie, in their integrity in their inward man, though through the infirmity of their fleſh and ſtrength of temptation, there m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y be ſome ſin found in their outward man, which ſin, they do not with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to, nor approve in their inner man but do even hate the ſame, which eſtimation is by God inſpiredly recorded in <hi>John</hi> 1.47. <hi>Pſal</hi> 34.17. <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.1. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.1. <hi>James</hi> 3.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.8. and in divers other places: and yet you ſelf-proved, noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſinning quakers, (which largely and truely appears in this Treatiſe) are ſo boldned in impudency, that you dare to ſay in full effect, that all the Holy Saints aforeſaid, and all ſuch humble-confeſſing Saints, by their ſo fully and truly acknowledging, that they had ſin in them, even when they were born of God, were not onely teachers of a deluſion but alſo of a great deluſion of the Devil to maintain the Devil's Kingdom. Oh fearful!</p>
               <p>But behold my beloved, that all this already ſaid, doth not diſcover the full height of the quakers malicious iniquity; for in that their ſpeech a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, they have in a high manner blaſphemouſly ſeized upon the Holy Ghoſt himſelf alſo; for they (in that their ſpeech) have in full effect charged upon the Holy Ghoſt, that he is the chiefeſt ſupreme Teacher, not onely of a deluſion, but alſo of a great deluſion of the Devil, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Devils Kingdom by his, the Holy Ghoſts, inſpiring, and thereby teaching all the Holy Saints aforeſaid, and all other ſuch, ſo humbly and faithfully to acknowledge, that they had ſin in them even when they were born of God; and by his inſpiredly teaching them to affirm, <hi>that there is no man that ſinneth not</hi> 1 King. 8.46. 2 Cor. 6.36. and alſo, <hi>that there is not a juſt man upon earth, that doth good, and ſinneth not,</hi> Eccleſ. 7.20.</p>
               <p>And now this their fearful blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt himſelf, being conſidered on, and how fearfully the quakers, I ſay, the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers becauſe it is evident that they do highly eſteem of that blaſphemous book of <hi>James Parnel</hi>'s: now conſidering that therein they have alſo fearfully blaſphemed againſt the Holy Ghoſts teachings in the Scriptures, they in full effect counting thoſe Goſpel-Scriptures not to be fitted by the Holy Ghoſt for any mans benefit; but for the devil to take up un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ered to maintain his, the Devils kingdom: and alſo noting, that they have
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100246:27"/> therein ſo horribly blaſphemed againſt the Goſpel precious vertues of Chriſt's death and blood ſhed; and obſerving, that they have audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly affronted (if not blaſphemed) againſt the whole Trinity; which appears in full effect in my fourth Diſcourſe; and conſidering, how they are proved to be of thoſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, ſhewing falſe ſigns and wonders in my tenth Diſcourſe: and alſo conſidering, that they have made it manifeſt in their Doctrines which are in the Treatiſe detected, That they have trodden under foot the Son of God, and do count the blood of the Covenant an unholy thing, and that they do deſpite the Spirit of Grace, theſe being the three marks appropriated to diſcover the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, which is in full effect ſhewed in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. and noting therewith, how the quakers have from their own preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wicked perſonal facts in full effect, adjudged themſelves to be of the Devil and not of Chriſt, which appears evidently in my ſecond Diſcourſe: and conſidering alſo, that it is very well known, that very many of them (if not all of them) have not onely received the knowledge of the Truth; but have alſo been profeſſors of the ſame before they were quakers: but now they be fallen away from the Truth, ſee how apparently all thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive marks are found upon them, that are mentioned in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. from the 26 to the 31 <hi>verſ.</hi> It appears by, and in all theſe reſpects, and many other in this Treatiſe appearing that they, the quakers are not onely of the falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets aforeſaid, but alſo they (the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers) are acting in the great and unpardonable ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt and that they ſo perſiſting, will run themſelves unpardonably into the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting fearful curſes thereto belonging; notwithſtanding whatſoever they are over-powered to conceit of themſelves to the contrary.</p>
               <p>And now thou <hi>James Nayler</hi> haſt ſtopped thine own mouth, from ever again uttering forth ſuch a proud <hi>Goliah</hi>-like challenge, as thou haſt done, where thou in the 23 <hi>pag.</hi> of thy <hi>Satan's Deſign diſcovered,</hi> ſayeſt, <hi>And though we be counted the greateſt offenders that ever was in the whole world, by the heads of Sects; yet is there not one of you that is able nor willing to judge us, and our practice and judgement with the practice of the Saints in which they walked and plain Scriptures without meanings:</hi> This is thy haughty challenge, <hi>Iames.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now do you note, That you quakers your own ſelves, have even totally ſpared your Oppoſers that labour to judge you by the practice of the Saints, which they have walked in: for by your undeniable numerous preſumptuous ſins of your perſonal facts and falſe Doctrines, you quakers have made it ſo manifeſt, even againſt your own ſelves, that you do walk
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100246:27"/> in ſuch notorious preſumptuous ſins, which the Saints practiſed not, which appears fully and truly in this Treatiſe, that there is no need at all, no, not in the leaſt meaſure, for your Oppoſers to bring Scriptures, neither with meanings, nor without meanings, to prove that over again which you have already ſo cleerly and firmly proved againſt your own ſelves, that you quakers do walk in many notorious wicked practices, even in a full affronting direct oppoſition againſt, and quite contrary to, the Saints practice; and yet to make more ſure work totally, to ſpare your Oppoſers that labour, Satan, thy Maſter, <hi>James,</hi> hath exalted thee to be the Judge <hi>James,</hi> in this cauſe; and by thine own, and the other quakers notorious preſumptious ſins (though lurking under your outward gliſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing varniſh, yet) judiciouſly to condemn thy ſelf <hi>James,</hi> and all them alſo, to be lyers, and ſo not abiders in the truth; and ſo, that thou and they alſo, are of the devil, and not of Chriſt, which appears by thine own juſt law, <hi>James,</hi> by me related in thine own words in my ſecond Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p>And thus thou thy ſelf <hi>James,</hi> haſt made that thy aforeſaid vaunting challenge not onely frivilous, but ridiculous alſo. And now conſidering that you ſinful quakers do refuſe the gracious help of the Goſpel imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I am conſtrained to leave you all under the juſtneſs of your brother quaker, <hi>James Naylers</hi> fiery condemnation aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>And as for your thundring out ſevere charges, and threatning fearful curſes in print in full effect, againſt all men that do oppoſe your quakery, know all you quakers, that I do ſet them all as light as levity it ſelf, even to be as ayry as your quakiſh legal couzen (ing) German the Popes roaring bulls, and curſings with Bell, Book, and Candle; for in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of my God, who knoweth the truth hereof, I do affirm, (as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſomewhat touched) That he, my heavenly Father for my humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and inſtruction hath formerly permitted the Devil, to exerciſe his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſms and ſeeming heavenly joys, and ſpeaking-voyces in me, and to work his powerful quakiſh temptations in me diſtinctly, as it were ſtep by ſtep, even in the ſame manner, that he, the Devil, doth now act and ſpeak in you quakers; and doth thereby teach you, and over-rule you, and deceive you quakers, and doth alſo by permiſſion thereby enable you to deceive others alſo. And (but for brevity ſake) I would relate at large the particular quakiſh gradations of the Devils former works in me: how he would have perſwaded me that I was Chriſt; and he falling in that, how he would have over-power me to believe that I ſhould be a great admired Prophet, and many other quakiſh luciferian exaltations, he would have powerfully-faſtned on me, and in me, ſutably to the ſame or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:100246:28"/> without Scripture-warrant, even as he doth now work in all deceive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs, in you quakers: and how that after the Devil found, that my merciful heavenly Father would not permit any of his quakiſh luciferian exaltations to reſt in me, to work my eternal deſtruction; then the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil with great violence flew at my perſon, and would at two ſeveral times have ſtrangled me in my throat to death: ſo that it appears, the Devil intended that I ſhould never ſpeak more in this world; for had not my gracious God reſcued me out of the Devils claws, my body had then periſhed; for my life was very neer loſt at both thoſe his violent aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ults upon my perſon: and at his departure from me, he ſtroke me within my breſt ſo that it ſmarted about a quarter of an hour after: and alſo the Devil did therewith caſt into me a ſtrange, foul, noyſome taſte and ſmell, which continued in me about a quarter of an hour alſo; but the particulars at large of the Devils other manifold ſtrong quakiſh deluſions wrought in me, are too many here to recite: and although it hath pleaſed my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father out of his abundant mercy, (notwithſtanding my great un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs) totally and cleerly to deliver me, not onely out of the devils priding quakiſh exaltations, but alſo to reſcue my perſon out of the devils devouring jaws; yet ſtill (by thoſe my former inward experiences in thoſe the Devils ſubtil, flattering, powerful, and deſtructive quakiſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions, now by him exerciſed in you quakers) I am by meer Grace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to know your quakers conditions, and that by Satans ſpirit ſpeaking in you, (as he hath formerly done in me) you are over-powered, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded, and helliſhly ſnared; notwithſtanding the Devils falſe gliſtering varniſh glittering on you. And now I neither care nor fear in the leaſt, neither your quakers curſes, nor what any other man will cenſure of me, for this my ſhort Relation, becauſe my heavenly Fathers approbation in my conſcience, is contentedly in me ſound ſatisfaction in full.</p>
               <p>And now I am by the means aforeſaid, and other gracious helps, ſo ſenſible of mine own unability, and am ſo confident in my Lord Chriſt his gracious aſſiſtance, whoſe perſon is in heaven without you and me, that I could wiſh, that thou <hi>James Nayler</hi> couldſt (if thou haſt a ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack to it) exerciſe thy pen to declare what thou canſt do againſt me that am directly againſt all quakery: for notwithſtanding this my experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental warning fairly and faithfully given you, yet I do conjecture that you quakers will roar, for I ſee by your books, that you quakers can can ſcould tantara againſt the Truth; but I care not at all for that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for theſe three evident cauſes: firſt, becauſe you have behaved your ſelves ſo falſly already, that your foul tongues are no ſlander, although you would yet further ſlander with them. Secondly, becauſe I do ſee,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:100246:28"/> that you quakers have your own ſelves ſet the antichriſtian brand, ſo hard on, and ſo fiery-hot upon your ſelves, that that mark will remain to be ſeen fairly upon you quakers, when you have done roaring. Thirdly, becauſe I ſee, that the more you write, the more you diſcover your own ſhame and fooliſhneſs; and that thereby you do give your Oppoſers more and more advantage to point out your quakers manifold quakiſh ſtumblings, even quite out of all ſaving truths.</p>
               <p>Again, whereas you quakers do by your tenents affirm conſtanly in full effect, that Chriſt in his fleſh without men did not die at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for any mans Goſpel-juſtification before God the Father; but that Chriſt did die in his perſon of fleſh without men at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for mens examples onely, for men to learn and work in themſelves by that his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward example, patience, meekneſs, temperance, and ſuch-like holineſs. And ſecondly by your affirming in your tenents in full effect, That men cannot work in themſelves any perfect, holy, ſaving works by any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward example whatſoever ſet before them: no, ſaith your Doctrine, men themſelves cannot ſo work, no ſay you, therein; it muſt be Chriſt onely that muſt work perfect, holy, ſaving works in men, by his ſpiritual power alone, or elſe men cannot be ſaved. Now from theſe your ſayings, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compared together, I do ſtand to maintain againſt you quakers, that you muſt prove; I ſay again, if you will endeavor to ſupport your rotten quakery, you muſt prove by Scripture, That Chriſt the Son of God (and Creator of Heaven and Earth, and all things which are therein) was and is not able by his ſpiri ual power onely, to work perfect, holy, ſaving works in men, although <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e had never ſuffered in his tormenting death and blood ſhed, even as perfectly by his ſpiritual power in men, (if that could have ſatisfied his Fathers juſtice for mens ſins) as if he had died for mens out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward example onely a thouſand times over, as he eſtabliſhed all the holy elect Angels by his ſpiritual power onely without any relation to the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of his perſonal death and dloodſhed. Therefore, I ſay again, if you quakers cannot prove by plain Scriptures, That Chriſt the Son of God, he being God, was, and is not able by his ſpiritual power alone to work ſaving, perfect, holy works in men, although he had never ſuffered in his tormenting death and blood ſhed, onely to purchaſe an outward example for men to look on and learn by, onely to make themſelves ſavingly holy, you do not onely confute your ſelves in your aforeſaid Doctrine, which is, that no man can do that; but you do alſo therewith ſhew evidently, that your quakery doth maintain, that Chriſt did die abſolutely and in all reſpects totally in vain. I do acknowledge, you quakers, that Chriſt by his meekneſs, patience, and holineſs, ſhewed forth by him in his ſufferings
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:100246:29"/> and death, is our example; and that he doth ſay, <hi>Be ye holy, for I am holy:</hi> but it is firmly proved by Scriptures, and the holy Saints in their inward man; and yet confeſſing, that they had ſin remaining in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious outward man even when they were born of God; and that they were not free from ſin in them at any time in this their life upon earth; no, not at their finiſhing their courſe; and that it is God's permiſſion that ſo it ſhould be, even in the Saints outward man, or fleſh, for their humiliation, and the preſervation of the glory of his Goſpel-free-grace to himſelf: all which is proved ſo largely in my thirteenth Diſcourſe by Scriptures, that thereby it is evident, that that exhortation, <hi>Be ye holy, for I am holy,</hi> and all ſuch places are directed to the inward man in men, inlightned according to <hi>John</hi> 1.7, 8. and not to the outward man, or fleſh: for it is alſo firmely proved, that that is ſo rebellious in it ſelf, that it cannot receive any holy exhortations: therefore your quakers affirming in full effect, that Chriſt died for mens examples onely that men might work in themſelves by that outward pattern, perfect, holy, ſaving works both in their inward and outward man alſo. I affirm yet once again, That if you quakers cannot prove that Chriſt was, and is unable by his Spirit alone to work thoſe works in man, although he never died for mens outward example onely, that then you do evidently maintain, that Chriſt did ſuffer in his bitter and terrible tormenting death, abſolutely, and in all reſpects totally in vain; and ſo it appears that you quakers are to eat up you former words, and then affirm, That there never was any Chriſt that died at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and ſo, that there never was any Chriſt in the world, that ever had, or hath any perſon of fleſh, ſaving onely your own perſonal quaking Chriſts, now come into the world in your fleſh. And by your affirming, That Chriſt had no Body but his Church, which is firmly proved againſt you in my eleventh Diſcourſe it doth appear that the laſt ſenſe is your choice mark. And now do you quakers lay your heads together, and ſee what you can pick out of this bone.</p>
               <p>Again, you quakers, whereas you do affirm in your Doctrines in full effect, that if any man have the leaſt ſin, or any ſin remaining in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that that man cannot then be poſſibly ſaved, becauſe that man, whilſt he hath any ſin in him, is of the Devil and not of Chriſt. And in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, I do alſo ſtand to maintain againſt all you quakers, that if you will endeavor to ſupport your quaking reputation, you muſt even upon ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity prove by plain Scripture, that your notorious lying, foul-mouthed ſlandering, cowardly backbiting, diſſembling equivocating, falſifying in print of the very words of holy Scriptures to deceive people withal, falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:100246:29"/> in print your Oppoſers words, they being printed alſo, your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of the plain and true ſenſe of the holy Scriptures deſtructively to delude people withal, and your fearful blaſphemies: I ſay again, That if you quakers do not prove by plain Scriptures unfalſified, that thoſe your ſelf-proved, manifold high preſumptuous tranſgreſſions, both againſt God and man alſo, are nor any ſins, and are no ſins in you quakers, then I affirm, that you your own ſelves, by your own apparent practices in thoſe high preſumptuous tranſgreſſions aforeſaid, both againſt God and man alſo, do render up your own ſelves by reaſon of thoſe high preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptious ſins in your perſons to be utterly and totally uncapable of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and you by your own judgement, by you paſſed upon your ſelves, are of the Devil, and not of Chriſt; for you quakers have made it ſo manifeſtly apparent, that you do ſtand guilty before God in thoſe noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious high preſumptious ſins aforeſaid, which appears by your own evil behaviours, ſo firmly proved in this Treatiſe, that it cannot be any ways ſtronglier proved, then to ſhew your books, and your Oppoſers, and Scripture falſified by you; eſpecially, becauſe you ſinful quakers do totally refuſe the gracious help of the Goſpel gracious imputation. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I adviſe you quakers to look about you quickly, and to lay your heads together again, to ſtudy it out, how to prove by plain Scriptures unfalſified, that thoſe your notorious, high preſumptious, ſelf-proved tranſgreſſions aforeſaid, are not any ſins, and are no ſins in you, even upon your everlaſting peril aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>And as for your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooking in the word <hi>faith</hi> for a faſhion into your qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers language, it is evident by Scripture-doctrine, that <hi>faith</hi> can be no other in your legal profeſſion, nor no other ways but a falſe gloſs, and a uſeleſs ſuperfluous hang by if you do make light uſe of any kinde of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ith at all; for by your conſiding to be ſaved by moral works wrought in you you do thereby make your pretended faith for a gloſs, vain, frivilous, void and of none effect.</p>
               <p>And my beloved, tender-hearted, ſeeking, unſetled ones you have no cauſe to be diſmaded in the leaſt meaſure at the quakers ſuffering for their quakery; for as there is a ſpirit of Truth, ſo there is a ſpirit of error al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo according to 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.6. and that man or woman that is by grace pofeſſed in them with God's Spirit of Truth, is inabled by that holy Spirit working powerfully in them (when occaſion for God's cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it) to ſuffer even death it ſelf for the Truths ſake; witneſs the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſufferings of all the holy Saints and Martyrs in all ages: and on the contrary, that man or woman that is by Gods juſt puniſhment poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed in them with the devils ſpirit of error, is enabled by that wicked
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:100246:30"/> ſpirit working powerfully in them (when occaſion for the Devils cauſe requires it) to ſuffer even death it ſelf for their errors ſake; witneſs the ſufferrings of all erronious wicked Hereticks in all ages. But thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that contentedly remain onely in their natural, wilful ignorance and blindneſs; and not being poſſeſſed with one of thoſe two powerful ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in them, cannot poſſibly ſuffer neither for truth nor error, witneſs thoſe vaſt multitudes of unſtable, weak-minded men and women that were profeſſors for Popery, in ſome part of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8 his raign; and yet eaſily turned for Proteſtants and directly againſt Popery in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s raign; and yet did all readily turn again directly againſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and for Popery in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s raign. And doubtleſs, very many of the very ſame perſons did live in Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> raign, who then as readily turned again directly againſt Popery and for Proteſtants again. Therefore my beloved ones, conſider well both of the powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Spirit of Truth and ſpirit of error in them that are poſſeſſed in them with any of thoſe two powerful ſpirits, and how unable all the reſt of the people of the world are, to ſuffer either for God's Truth, or the Devils inſpired error.</p>
               <p>Neither you, my beloved, tender-hearted, ſeeking, unſettled ones, have any cauſe at all to be diſcouraged in the leaſt meaſure at the quakers mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous ſigns and wonders: firſt, becauſe our bleſſed Saviour hath fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told us, that the falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets which ſhould come into the world, ſhould ſhew ſuch deceivable ſigns and wonders; and becauſe the quakers do ſay, that they are Chriſt, and becauſe our bleſſed Saviour hath ſo lovingly given us ſuch punctual warning to take heed and beware of ſuch deceivers, of which ſort of deceivers, the quakers have made themſelves manifeſtly appear to be, which is proved in my tenth D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcourſe. And ſecondly, becauſe the erronious <hi>Theadas</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> did draw much people after them, even as the ſelf-proved erronious quakers do now; and becauſe <hi>Simon Magus</hi> by his having bewitched the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with his Sorceries along time, the people ſaid, <hi>This man is the great power of God,</hi> even as much people now, being bewitched with quakiſh Sorceries, do magnifie the quakers even unto a luciferian height; and becauſe the Inchanters and ſatanical Magicians of <hi>Egypt,</hi> did by permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion work ſome of thoſe miraculous ſigns and wonders by the power of the Devil in <hi>Egypt,</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> did work in <hi>Egypt</hi> by the powerful finger of God, which appears in <hi>Exod.</hi> 10, 11 <hi>chap.</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is written, That <hi>there are ſome whoſe coming is, after the working of the power of Satan, with all power and ſigns and lying wonders,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.9. And now my beloved ones conſider ſeriouſly, that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:100246:30"/> the Devils inſtruments can by the Devils power and permiſſion, work de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful miraculous ſigns and wonders, even as is deceitfully wrought at the quakers meetings and preachings, even ſo powerful beloved, as ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive (if it were poſſible) the very elect.</p>
               <p>And now my Reader, I pray thee to note ſeriouſly, that in <hi>James Naylers</hi> before recited ſevere ſentence of condemning all Chriſtians that have any ſin to be found in them; in theſe words of his, <hi>But who ſays they know Chriſt, and are redeemed and commit ſin, not keeping his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments is a lyer, and ſo abides not in the truth and anoynting and ſo is of the devil, and not of Chriſt.</hi> Theſe be his words. And now I pray thee obſerve that he is led not onely according to his uſe falſly to add words to that Text, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.4. but alſo, although our Saviour Chriſt hath made a cleer diſtinction, betwixt his Goſpel-commands, and his Fathers moral Law-commands, where he ſaith, <hi>If ye keep my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, ye ſhall abide in my love even as I have kept my Fathers commandments, and abide in his love,</hi> John 15.10. and although this diſtinction ſets forth a true abiding in the Doctrine of Chriſt, as (but for brevity ſake) I could by Scripture ſhew much more largely yet <hi>James Nayler,</hi> as aforeſaid, is ſatanically overpowered to confound into one law, the Fathers killing moral law written on Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and Chriſts mount <hi>Sinai</hi>'s healing Goſpel-law of life, which runs in this and the like gracious tenure, <hi>He that believeth on him that juſtifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteouſneſs, Rom.</hi> 4 5 But as <hi>James</hi> hath done, ſo whilſt he remains a quaker he muſt confound the Goſpel-law and the moral law into one and the ſame law, or elſe, as quakery cannot ſtand, ſo <hi>James Nayler</hi> and the quakers could not ſo eaſily make choice of moral law works to be wrought in mens bodies for their ſaluation, and ſo alſo the devil would fall ſhort by his quakers to declare, that they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are notorious ſinners, and yet do deny the Goſpel-imputation, and that ſo they themſelves are of the Devil, and not of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="discourse">
               <head>FOURTEENTHLY,</head>
               <p>My fourteenth Diſcourſe is directed to all the quakers; for you qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers conſidering the plain evidences, that your quakiſh conducters have publiſhed, by their, as it were, throwing filthy ſtinking mire and dirt in the very face of all quakery. Now you quakers haue a juſt cauſe not onely to howl, but to howl out loud; for it appears that you quakers are very expert in howling: for <hi>John Gilpin</hi> in the 3 <hi>pag.</hi> of his book <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e calls the quakers ſhaken, printed <hi>London,</hi> 1655. affirmeth, that whilſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:100246:31"/> he was a quaker, he was conſtrained to fall down on his bed where he howl'd in a terrible and hiddeous manner, to the great aſtoniſhment of his family, which he alſo there ſaith, is uſual with them (to wit, the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers) and alſo Mr. <hi>Samuel Clark</hi> in his 461 <hi>pag.</hi> of his book he inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>A Mirror or Looking-glaſs</hi> doth declare, That in <hi>anno Chriſti,</hi> 1653. there came ſome quakers out of the North into <hi>Wales,</hi> to win ſome Profeſſors to their party boaſting themſelves were perfect and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin (which ſome of the principalleſt quakers here have affirmed of themſelves in my hearing) and he declareth, That at thoſe quakers meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there, after long ſilence, had ſuch riſings and ſwellings in their bowels, ſending forth ſuch ſhreekings, yellings, and howlings, as not onely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted the Spectators, but cauſed the dogs to bark, the ſwine to cry, ond the cattel to run about, to the aſtoniſhment of all that heard them: but it can no ways be proved, that people have ſhreeked as Night-Owls, yelled as infernal Syirits, and have howl'd as devoured dogs and wolves at peoples meetings at the preachings of the true Goſpel of our bleſſed Chriſt, and far much more leſs, that dogs, and ſwine, and other cattel, are then are thereby forc'd into ſuch a violent diſtempered rage nor that little children, who are utterly uncapable to underſtand, either what is done or ſaid, at the preaching of the true Goſpel, do fall down and roar, and their bellies ſwell, and foam at the mouth then, and thereby, as appears, that beſides men and women ſo tormented, that even little children, alſo are in that manner fearfully tormented, at the quakers meetings or preachings of quakery, which the quakers do not deny though it be charged upon them, which appears in <hi>Saul's Errand.</hi> And I now acknowledging my ſelf to be really a very unworthy Servant of my bleſſed Lord Jeſus Chriſt; yet I remain unto all true Goſpel-believers, and conſiders in my bleſſed Lord Jeſus his death, and precious blood ſhed without men; and alſo to all them that do deſire ſo to believe,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Their affectionate and officious Servant in Chriſt, <hi>Chriſtopher Wade.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:100246:31"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>NOte, That all <hi>James Nayler</hi>'s proud Luciferian behaviours, &amp; all his diſciples blaſphemous exaltations of <hi>James Nayler</hi> at <hi>Briſtol,</hi> even with no leſs then divine titles, as appears in print, are all of them ſtrong confirmations of the juſtneſs of all the accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are charged upon the quakers in this precedent Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>And it is to be marvelled at, That conſidering the Scriptures do fight ſo fiercely againſt all your quakery, that you quakers do not quite forſake all and any uſe of the Scriptures, to ſupport you: and why you do not act from your enthuſiaſms only and alone, and in your wandring courſes to knock your hand upon your breſt, and ſay, Here, here 'tis; and then continue to tell the people a long ſtory, that you are ſent from heaven, and are taught from heaven: but then it will be alſo to be wondred at, how exceeding ignorant thoſe people muſt be, that will believe you. And concerning your Myſtery you ſo much boaſt of, know, all you quakers, That the Myſtery of God's will concerning men, is not lock'd up in quakery; but is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by the Scriptures of the Prophets, <hi>Rom. 16.25, 26.</hi> and is alſo made manifeſt by the Apoſtles: ſee <hi>Epheſ. 3.7, 9. Epheſ. 1.9. Col. 1.26.</hi> but you quakers know it not.</p>
            <p>And now, my Reader, thou mayeſt take notice conveniently, That ſince my finiſhing of this my foregoing Treatiſe, there is by provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence come to my hands two ſhort books, printed; both of them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to be compoſed by the joynt conſent of two men, whoſe names are, as they therein ſay, <hi>John Reve,</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleton,</hi> who ſay, That <hi>they are taught by immediate revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from Chriſt himſelf, as appears, without God's medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate help by his Scriptures,</hi> (even as the quakers do in full effect ſay;) they pretend alſo, that <hi>they onely are the two Witneſſes of God mentioned in the</hi> Re elations: they do ſay, That their commiſsion is to this effect, they ſaying, <hi>God hath choſen us two</hi> onely, <hi>and hath put the two-edged ſword of his Spirit into mouths, that whom we are made to pronounce bleſſed, are bleſſed to eternity; and whom we are made to pronounce
<pb facs="tcp:100246:32"/> curſed, are curſed to eternity: and his power</hi> (ſay they) <hi>no mortal can take out of our hands, neither will our God any more give ſuch power to men while the world indures.</hi> Theſe be their words. They ſay alſo, That they were ſent to <hi>New-gate</hi> by the then Lord Major of <hi>London,</hi> in <hi>Sept. anno Dom. 1653.</hi> And I finde, that they have their wandring walking diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to carry abroad their doctrine and books; for by that means theſe two books came to my hands, even as the wandring quakers do diſperſe abroad their doctrines and books; and thoſe two pretended witneſſes of God, their doctrines are alſo fearfully blaſphemous (though they are no quakers:) but for brevity ſake I ſhall give but a hint of them; they affirm in very plain and full effect, That God the Father came down with his Son Chriſt unto the earth, and abode with him upon the earth, during all the time of his continuance thereon; and that the perſonal preſence of God, was all the time of his Sons being on earth, wholly abſent from the Angels, whom he left in the heavens above the ſtars. All which is flat contrary to <hi>John 4.9.</hi> and <hi>John 5.37.</hi> therein being ſaid, That <hi>God ſent his Son into the world:</hi> which proves fully againſt them, that God the Father did not come in his ſpiritual perſonal eſſence with his Son unto the earth; and they alſo thereby do fight againſt the truth of <hi>Mat. 10.32.</hi> and <hi>Mat. 12.20.</hi> where our Saviour, even when he was on the earth, even then ſaid, <hi>My Father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> which firmly proveth again, That God his Father was not in his ſpiritual perſon with Chriſt his Son upon the earth. And they ſay, That God the Father whilſt he was abſent from the Angels in heaven, did then give the Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> a commiſsion, to repreſent the glorious perſon of the Creator in heaven, whilſt he was with his Son on earth: which their ſaying, doth audaciouſly affront, <hi>Iſa. 42.8.</hi> where God ſaith, he <hi>will not give his glory to another.</hi> It's marvel, that they do not imagine with their moon-eyes, that the man ſaid to be in the Moon, is God: and they in very full effect ſay accordingly, That Jeſus in all his extreamities, cried to the Prophet <hi>Eliah,</hi> he being then an immortal God, and Father in glory: and that the Prophet <hi>Eliah,</hi> as a faithful Steward with
<pb facs="tcp:100246:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> did from the Throne of Glory, miniſter conſolation unto his Lord and Saviour in mortality; and that the whole Godhead was dead and buried for a moment; and that if any man prayes unto any God or Father, but unto the Man Jeſus, he prayes unto his own lying imagination, which is the Devil; which is a deſperate contradiction againſt the bleſſed Man Jeſus his own commands, <hi>John 16.23.</hi> and <hi>John 15.16.</hi> wherein our Saviour doth not direct men to pray to himſelf, the Man Jeſus; but he doth direct men to ask of his Father in his Name. And they ſay, That there is no Creator, nor God, nor never was, but the Man Jeſus; which their ſaying is a blaſphemous denial of the Holy Trinity, and is flat contrary to <hi>Gen. 1.26.</hi> wherein it's ſaid in the plural number, <hi>Let us make man in our image.</hi> And truely, beloved, I finde little or none other Doctrine in their two books; but ſuch brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick fantaſtical ſtories, which proveth to veiw, that the aforeſaid Witneſſes <hi>John Reve,</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Muggleton,</hi> are the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and not Gods Witneſſes. And, my beloved, I think it not fit to ſet any more of their noyſome ſilthy ſtuff before thee; onely I ſhall give thee a little notice, how far the two Witneſſes Doctrines are making open wars againſt the quakers teachings, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the two Witneſſes ſay, That heaven is beyond the ſtars, and ſo without men; but the quakers do in their doctrines affirm the flat contrary, and do ſay therein, That heaven is not without men, but is in mens bodies: the two Witneſſes do affirm, that the Man Jeſus, in his body of fleſh and bone, is aſcended far above all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, Angels and men; but the quakers in their doctrines do deny that, and do affirm in full effect to the flat contrary, that Chriſt is not aſcended into any heaven without men, but that Chriſts perſon of fleſh is in mens bodies God and Man. And I could ſhew many other ways, how punctually thoſe two Witneſſes do prove the quakers to be deluding lyers; and how expreſsly the quakers do affirm, that thoſe two witneſſes are lying deluders. And truely, beloved, I would not have done ſo much, as once to have put pen to paper abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> theſe two frantick pretended Witneſſes of God; but only becauſe, that there is not in the whole Chriſtian world, that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, any
<pb facs="tcp:100246:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> other people, that ſay they are taught immediately by Chriſt himſelf, without the mediate uſe of Chriſts inſpired Scriptures; but theſe two ſorts of people only, the two witneſſes and and the quakers, and yet they one contradicting another, and proving one another in full effect, to be devil-like deluders, they both confirming that to be true of one another by both their helliſh doctrines, which doubtleſs for helliſhneſs, cannot be fully ſampled by any other people but they, the witneſſes and quakers onely, in the whole Chriſtian world; and they both have blaſphemouſly fathered their Satan-like doctrine and helliſh lyes upon our bleſſed Saviour Chriſts own immediate teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, though they are both ſo flat contrary one to the other in falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bood, thereby they both rendring up in full effect our bleſſed Lord Chriſt, to be the ſupreme Author of confuſion, and the chiefeſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of helliſh lyes. All which ſhews plainly, beloved, by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils over-ruling both theſe ſorts of people, being both for immediate enthuſiaſms, how exceeding dangerous it is for any man to truſt to immediate revelations, not iſſuing from the mediate uſe of Gods Word, the Scriptures; for by that his teaching, the Devil hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the quakers falſe Chriſt in men, and the two Witneſſes falſe Chriſt without men, to pleaſe every mans palate what he can, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to lay his helliſh ſnares the more numerouſly abroad, to deſtroy eternally as many people as he poſsibly can, who are ſeeking to enjoy the heavenly benefits of our bleſſed Chriſt. And now the good and gracious all-ſeeing God of heaven and earth, in mercy preſerve all tender-hearted, ſeeking, unſettled Chriſtians out of theſe manifold eternally deſtructive ſecret ſnares of the Devil, the inveterate ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of God and all his Servants.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100246:33"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
